<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The earth twice shaken wonderfully, or, An analogical discourse of earthquakes its natural causes, kinds, and manifold effects : occasioned by the last of these, which happened on the eighth day of September 1692, at two of the clock in the afternoon : divided into philosophical theorems, pick'd out of many famous, modern, and ancient treatises, translated into English : with reference to that unusual one that happened in Queen Elizabeth's reign, on the same day, 8th of September 1601 ... : with an account of many stupendious and wonderful events in Germany, Italy, and other kingdoms ... / by J.D.R., French minister.</title>
            <author>J. D. R., French minister.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R37</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4234</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12375991</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12375991</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60606</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58144)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60606)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 224:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The earth twice shaken wonderfully, or, An analogical discourse of earthquakes its natural causes, kinds, and manifold effects : occasioned by the last of these, which happened on the eighth day of September 1692, at two of the clock in the afternoon : divided into philosophical theorems, pick'd out of many famous, modern, and ancient treatises, translated into English : with reference to that unusual one that happened in Queen Elizabeth's reign, on the same day, 8th of September 1601 ... : with an account of many stupendious and wonderful events in Germany, Italy, and other kingdoms ... / by J.D.R., French minister.</title>
                  <author>J. D. R., French minister.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author ... and to be sold at Mr. Cockrel ... and at Mr. Vaillant ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693/4 [i.e. 1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Earthquakes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60606:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60606:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Earth twice ſhaken wonderfully:</p>
            <p>OR, AN Analogical Diſcourſe of Earthquakes, its Natural <hi>Cauſes, Kinds,</hi> and manifold <hi>Effects;</hi> OCCASIONED By the laſt of theſe, which happened on the Eighth Day of <hi>September</hi> 1692. at Two of the Clock in the Afternoon.</p>
            <p>Divided into <hi>Philoſophical Theorems,</hi> pick'd out of many Famous, Modern, and Ancient TREATISES, Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh;</hi> With Reference to that unuſual One, that happened in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, on the ſame Day, 8th. of <hi>September</hi> 1601. at the ſame Hour, which was ſenſibly felt throughout all <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſome part of <hi>Aſia</hi> in the ſame Moment, as much as it is found out.</p>
            <p>A DORNED, With an Account of many ſtupendious and wonderful Events in <hi>Germany, Italy,</hi> and other Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Some <hi>Obſervations</hi> are made upon the <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> wherein theſe Two Earthquakes agree, and the others wherein they differ.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. D. R.</hi> French Miniſter.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joel 3.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord ſhall roar out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and utter his Voice from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Heavens and the Earth ſhall ſhake; but the Lord will be the Hope of his People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, at <hi>Sion</hi>'s <hi>Colledge,</hi> near <hi>Cripplegate;</hi> and to be Sold at Mr. <hi>Cockrel,</hi> Bookſeller, at the Sign of the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> and at Mr. <hi>Vaillant,</hi> French Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, in the <hi>Strand,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>French Savoy</hi>'s Church, 1693/4.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:60606:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> 1693/4. </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Edward Cooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60606:2"/>
            <head>For the ever Honoured and Worthy <hi>Thomas Brown,</hi> of <hi>Alſey,</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Bedford</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> a Member of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, in this preſent Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TIS the cuſtom with thoſe that Dedicate any thing, to adorn their Frontiſpieces with the Panegyrick Praiſes of their <hi>Mecenas.</hi> In which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y create Favours, and Illuſtrate their own Eloquence, unto which I was always averſe. But, foraſmuch as the great Demonſtrations of your Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Benevolence towards my Family, are always in my Memory; <hi>my Affections could not but be moved with the Earth,</hi> and the Divine Providence at laſt afforded me an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which I had long ſought for in vain, to repay ſome ſmall acknowledgment of a grateful Mind, by offering unto you the firſt Fruits of a new Language (the Knowle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge of which I attained to in your Neighbourhood) then Dedicate any thing new to you. Nay, 'tis very reaſonable that this Treatiſe ſhould ſee again the ſame Country where it began to ſpeak, or rather to ſtut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Yet if there were any need to mention more weighty Reaſons and paſs by theſe, how innumerable of them, might be afforded, known both to me and the whole Nation, <hi>in the enumerating of which a whole Volum might be defective?</hi> But that
<pb facs="tcp:60606:3"/>which hath been the greateſt Motive with me, was the Piety innate to all your Noble Family, and to your Illuſtrious Lady, excelling all others both in Beauty of Body, and in great Parts of Mind. To which may be added the Candor and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of your Mind, free from all ſecular blemiſh; which Vertues you know how prudently to uſe in the exerciſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and the diſtribution of Right to every one, in puniſhing Vice and Vicious Perſons. On which, and on many other things is founded His Majeſty's (the moſt Prudent of Kings) and his Counſel, Judgment, in conferring on you the Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. The unanimous Concord of the whole Country in chuſing you to ſuſtain their Parts in the moſt <hi>Auguſt Engliſh</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was upheld by this Foundation. On this incorrupted Sincerity, leans the hope of its Patronage, and the Affection of a ſincere and faithful Mind, for the Conſervation and Promotion of the Preſent State of Affairs. But many Words become not the Candidate of a Foreign Tongue, eſpecially in ſo ſublime a Matter. Pray, Sir, reſpect not ſo much the external Meanneſs of the Perſon, as the Gratitude of his inmoſt Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, after the Example of that Prince who diſdained not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to accept of cold Water offered to him in the Hand of a Countryman, his Subject; But having peruſed this Work, be pleaſed to accept of it as a Pledge of the eternal Deference I owe to you, and diſdain not to embrace it in your Patronage. In the mean time that God will grant an Accompliſhment of this, and many other Years attended with his moſt gracious Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to you and all your honour'd Family, and that the effluxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Age may be free from all Commotion and fatal Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, either of the Earth, or of the Preſent Affairs of this Kingdom, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt devoted humble Servant, J. D. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April <hi>9. 1693.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:60606:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THAT common Saying, Objects move Powers, doth not want its Foundation. An Earthquake hath ſerved for the Subject Matter, for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of ſo many and ſo great Wits in Old Times, that it may ſeem needleſs to bring it upon the Stage again: The Earth was no ſooner ſhook on the 8th. of <hi>September</hi> laſt, but that, that ſtupendious Event became the common Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Diſcourſe and Writings of the Learned Men of this Nation. I betook alſo my ſelf to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration thereof, and ſo ſet out the following <hi>Engliſh</hi> Treatiſe, for my private improvement in this Tongue, without any deſign of publiſhing it, which ſhould never have come in print, had I not been overcome by the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of many qualified Perſons, and of ſeveral others of no ordinary Learning, to whoſe Notice it came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my Privity, when it was finiſhed; which was about the end of <hi>December</hi> laſt, and before the Evangelical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to Repentance, occaſioned by the Earthquake
<pb facs="tcp:60606:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:60606:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:60606:5"/>writ by Mr. <hi>Beverly,</hi> and the Book of the Learned Mr. <hi>Ray,</hi> concerning the Changes in the World, came forth.</p>
            <p>And altho' it ſeems, that I ought now to be more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt printing this Treatiſe, by how much the more the number of Writers upon this Subject is increaſed, yet many things being left untouch'd by them, which may give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to Publick Curioſity, and to the Wits of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to exerciſe themſelves about, I have here yield to propound to the World. And as there are many Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in which the late Earthquake ſeems to agree with that, which happened in the Year 1601. both in the Conjunction of Conſtellations, and the Influence of the Planets, if we may credit Mr. <hi>Patridge;</hi> I thought it not amiſs for the ſatisfaction of the Reader, to give him my thoughts thereon; though I do proteſt that I am very averſe to the Obſervation of Omens, and that I am of a very different Opinion from thoſe who have dared to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel that ſuch an Earthquake will be itterated here, as was in <hi>Sicily.</hi> God forbid that we ſhould by our ſins draw down his Judgments ſo heavily upon our own Heads, but rather in our Prayers to beg that God Almighty the Maker and Upholder of Heaven and Earth, would be pleaſed to grant unto our Monarch and Monarchy the moſt flouriſhing Proſperity, that the Conſtitution of this Kingdom and theſe happy Iſlands may be at quiet, firm and unmoveable till the end of Ages.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60606:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>That all Earthquakes in themſelves, are contrary to Nature. Their Conſideration is lawful.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label> HOw many ſorts of Earthquakes there are? and in regard of Natural Cauſes, what ſorts of Earthquake this was that we ſpeak of, as well in regard of its Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as in regard of its Effects. <hi>pag. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label> What was the neareſt natural Cauſe of this Earthquake, as in regard of its breadth, as in regard of its celerity, <hi>videl.</hi> the qualities and diſpoſitions of ſome fiery and ſubtil Vapours, hidden towards the Center of the Earth. To which may be added the various influences of the Celeſtial Bodies, as far as their qualities do prevail or reſiſt. <hi>pag. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:60606:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label> The Earthquake by its Nature hath not an end properly; yet the effects thereof are commonly three ſpecially evinced both by Experiences and Obſervations of Examples, to wit, Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Inundation and Sterility. To which ſome would joyn the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſages of ſome wonderful and unuſual Changes, <hi>&amp;c. pag. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. IV.</label> An examination of the Circumſtances wherein theſe two Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes do agree or differ, both in their Form and ſecond Cauſes, in regard of the different Aſpects of Planets as well as in their effects. <hi>p. 30.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>As a Corollary, Ten Problems are ſet riſing Naturally from that Matter.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Whether that be true, which <hi>Pliny</hi> doth aſſert, that <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> are ſeldom ſhaken, by reaſon of the cold of the one, and the heat of the other? <hi>p. 33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Why Rivers decreaſe by Earthquakes? <hi>p. 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Why thoſe places that are either lying upon, or encompaſſed by the Sea or ſome River, be obnoxious to Earthquakes? <hi>p. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> What credit may one give to the relation of <hi>Plato,</hi> of the Iſland <hi>Atlantis,</hi> drowned by an Earthquake? <hi>p. 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Whether exteriour wind entring the Eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from above is able to move it? <hi>p. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Whether Subterraneous Exhaltations are generated by the Sun Beams? <hi>p. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Whether ſome more ſullen times of Earthquakes are to be appointed for any certain reaſons? <hi>p. 44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Why are Birds frighted in an Earthquake? <hi>p. 45.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Whether the Vaults in Houſes are ſafeſt against Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes? <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> If i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the late Earthquake is ſo ended, that the ſole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Countries through which it went, are ſecure from its itteration? <hi>p. 46.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60606:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EARTH Twice Shaken WONDERFULLY.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THEOREMS.</head>
               <p>AS Reſt is contrary to the Nature of Heaven, ſo is Motion againſt the Nature of the Earth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But in this they differ, that although no Natural Cauſe ſtops the Motion of the Heaven, yet it may give ſome Motion to the Earth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Heaven never reſted but once, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.13. ſince the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation that we know of, and then not totally neither, but only in that part which is a Vehicle to the ſolar Body; but the Earth is often moved.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And altho' the reſt of the Heaven be in it ſelf a thing as much to be wondered at, as Motion in the Earth; yet the later ſeems to move and terrifie mens minds more.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For the Earth doth more nearly touch us than Heaven, and we are more ſenſible of danger, when the Foundation of the World trembles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60606:7"/>and is ſhaken under us as tho' it were falling, then if any thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen above our heads, or that which was moved above us move no more.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Which Events as they do affect mens minds with a ſingular, and as it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re an amazing Admiration, ſo they excite and ſtir them up more dil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gently to enquire after the Cauſe of the which, beſides our own experience. <hi>Ariſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tle</hi> Witneſſeth in the <hi>1ſt.</hi> Book of his <hi>Metaphyſickt, Cap.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Becauſe of Admiration, Men began both now and of old to Philoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phize.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 Seeing therefore that, that Earthquake which formerly happened on the 8th of <hi>September,</hi> 1601. between one and two of the Clock at Night, ſtruck almoſt all the Inhabitants of <hi>Europe</hi> with Admiration. I doubt not but that which happened lately on the 8th. day of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> laſt, excites many to the ſearch of the Cauſe and Nature of them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Neither is this tracing, even of wonderful and unaccu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>omed Events, by their cauſes any ways diſpleaſing to God, ſeeing Effects themſelves are more clearly underſtood, when the Cauſe is known, and the clearer Knowledge of Divine Works, begets clearer notice of God himſelf, and excites in us a greater fear and awe of him: for clearneſs in the Underſtanding begets efficacy in the Will and Ardour in the Affections.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whilſt therefore the Learned communicate to the World their Thoughts and Obſervations of that unuſual Earthquake which no ſmall part of the World felt, which Obſervations they gather from the Remarks they make of the different Events that happened here and there, eſpecially ſince that Town in <hi>Jamaica</hi> was almoſt ſwollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by an Earthquake. I have been likewiſe prevailed upon to put forth ſomething that might be as an earneſt, if by chance, by the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of Opinions, the cauſe of this ſo ſtupendious an Event might more truly and plainly appear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. I ſhall diſtribute the whole Matter into Four Chapters. The Firſt of which ſhall be of the Kind and Form of this Earthquake; The next of the efficient Cauſes; and the Third of the Effects, and of their Signification and Preſage, at leaſt as ordinary and common. <hi>Fourth,</hi> To which ſhall be joyned an Examination of Unformity or Diſparity of one from another, both in their Form, and in their Cauſes and Effects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60606:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Kind and Form of this Earthquake.</head>
               <p n="2">II. THere are two ſorts of Earthquakes, Trembling and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſation. The differences of Earthquakes or their ſeveral Kinds, may be derived either from the Force of the Spirit iſſuing out of the Superficies of the Earth, or from the ſound then made, and from other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents and effects. Hence it is, that in <hi>Lib. de Mun.</hi> There are reckon'd eight ſorts of Earthquakes. <hi>Georgius Agricola lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de ortu ſubter.</hi> Makes four ſorts of 'em, a Trembling when it quivers lateraly; Concuſſion when 'tis moved on high and ſhelving <hi>(in ſublime &amp; devexum;)</hi> arietation when contrary blows ſhake it. Laſtly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination when it is rowled like Water and the Waves. But the ſame Author in his fourth Book of thoſe things that proceed out of the Earth, <hi>pag.</hi> 14. more accurately divides Earthquakes into ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and compounded, and then ſubdvides both into their Species. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> 2. <hi>Metaphys,</hi> reduces all ſorts of Earthquakes to two gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Heads, to wit <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a trembling and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pulſus,</hi> which diviſion I thought good to follow in this place.</p>
               <p n="12">12. A Trembling is a Motion of the Earth according to its Latitude to the right and left ſide. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the forecited place <hi>(ſays)</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> trembling is towards the ſides, and calls it alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſignifies to brandiſh: for the leaping of the Earth is, as it were, a brandiſhing. And this ſort of Earthquke is frequent, but <hi>Pulſus</hi> and <hi>Arietation,</hi> as they call them, are more ſeldom, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> teſtifieth in his ſecond Book of his <hi>Metaphys, chap.</hi> 8. Pulſus ſeldom ſhake the Earth, for beginnings are not ſo eaſily multiplied, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Pulſus</hi> is a motion of the Earth according to its Longitude, to wit, when it is moved up or down. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſays, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and divides it into <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Syſtole</hi> and <hi>Diaſtole:</hi> to wit, either when the Vapour or Exhalation going up with violence, heaps up great Piles like Mountains, or removes or breaks Mountains themſelves, or laſtly ſucks them into the Earth in its vaſts gaping, as <hi>Pliny,</hi> Speaks.</p>
               <p n="14">14. But that Earthquake whereof we have ſpoken in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was different according to the diverſity of places where i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60606:8"/>
               <p n="15">15. In plain places 'twas a Trembling, becauſe it ſhook the Earth l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eraly to the right and the left. Thoſe who then felt the Quaking, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>irm it to have been a lateral one, like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocking of a Cradle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe who lay in the ſame Bed, that night it happened, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re violently juſtled one againſt the other, the cloaths being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from ſide to ſide; but wheither or no, there were the ſame ſort of Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing in all the places where it was. I am not very farward to affirm. But on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be bold to conclude from the Event, that in moſt plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, the Earth was not violently thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt forward, but did moſtly tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble. And although this trembling <hi>(Tremor)</hi> be counted leſs peril<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous than either <hi>Pulſus,</hi> Arietation or Inclination, yet it doth not want its dangers, as thoſe ſpecially then experienced that lived in the higheſt H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſes and in Caſtles, from whence the Voices and Exclamations of the Guards, were heard every where throughout the Country, for when the Cradle is moved too much either to the right or left, there is danger of the Child's falling out, ſo when the Fondations or Buildings be moved laterally, both the Walls are in danger, eſpecially in Towers where the ſubſterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Spirit being included within the Arches, doth as it were, force the Tower more either to this or that ſide; otherwiſe the hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er the Walls are, the more ſenſible is the ſhaking (called, <hi>Vibratio.</hi>) This is certainly apparent from Hiſtory, that the Town of <hi>Scarp,</hi> not far diſtant from <hi>Florence,</hi> in the Valley of <hi>Magellum,</hi> between the <hi>Veſuvian</hi> and <hi>Apennine</hi> Mountains, in the year 154<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on the 3. of <hi>July</hi> did firſt Quake by ſuch a ſort of Vibration, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was ſo ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken, that moſt of the Houſes were ruined, great Cracks and Chinks being made in them, and 500 of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Inhabitants were d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtroyed, which Eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quake is related by <hi>Geor. Agricol. lib. de Natura rerum è terra effluentium pag</hi> 151. who Wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t his Book the ſame year the Town <hi>was made ruinous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tainous places, to this Trembling was added a <hi>Pulſe.</hi> Eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quakes are more noxious in Mountains than in Valleys, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y reaſon the more frequent ſubterraneous Cavities which there lye hid, into which the Spirits are more copiouſly gathered and prevail more ſtrong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, but eſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cially where the ſuper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icies is ſolidly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted and ſmoothly leve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led. <hi>Plinius lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. (ſays) <hi>Nec mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſa talicarent malo,</hi> neither do the Mountains are without ſuch an inconvenience (evil.) I am ſure the <hi>Alpes</hi> and <hi>Apennine</hi> Mountains h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbled, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve occaſion to that of <hi>Virgil Inſolitis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pes</hi> And the H. Scripture, ſays, <hi>Naham.</hi> 1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tains are move<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60606:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Switzerland</hi> alſo felt it at the very ſame time. A noted Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs of which ſpeaks after this manner. <q>Whilſt I was Travelling in <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland</hi> in <hi>September</hi> and <hi>October,</hi> I found Men's minds terrifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d more by that Earthquake, than I perce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ved they were in the more cloſe parts of <hi>Germany.</hi> And that it was no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a ſimple Trembling of the Earth, but a certain <hi>Pulſus</hi> and Concuſſion joyned with a Trembling, thoſe things that I ſaw eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y where in thoſe parts, the Effects of this Earthquake, ſufficiently demonſtrated to me, of which I will mention but one. There is a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gh and ſcraggy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain two Hours Journey diſtant from <hi>Lucern,</hi> not v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry remote from that ſtupendious Mountain which <hi>Pomponius Mela,</hi> call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Fractum Montem,</hi> the Vulgar (I know not by what ſort of ſuperſtition) <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat</hi>'s Mountains, but the Inhabitants call it <hi>Burka</hi> (if I do remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) under this Mountain on the Eight of <hi>September,</hi> about Two a Clock at Night, there aroſe a dreadful Bellowing and Fragor to the great Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſternation of the Inhabitants that live thereabouts, there were elevated into the Air, as it were thick Fumes, which filled all the Neighbourhood; at lenghth the greateſt part of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>op of the Mountain was broke off with a great noiſe, and tumbled down into the Lake of <hi>Lucern,</hi> which runs by it, but from the other part of the Mountain, which other People (called <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waldenſers</hi>) inhabit, ſome part alſo being violently thrown down, is reported to have buryed ſeven of the Inhabitants: ſo in the 85th. year of the laſt Age, part of the Mountain was broken off, three hours Journey diſtant from a certain Village called <hi>Hyborn,</hi> under the Juriſdiction of the Canton of <hi>Bern</hi>'s; ſituated above the Lake <hi>Lemanus,</hi> from which iſſued a vehement Wind, which carried with it Stones, Clods, and Trees; ſo that having paſſed over the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terjacent Hills, at the length the meſurable Village it ſelf was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed and oppreſſed which the Deſtruction of its Inbabitants.</q> The like Examples do every where occurr in Hiſtory and <hi>Seneca, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Nat. queſt,</hi> reports out of <hi>Thucidides,</hi> that <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>las</hi> was cleft and broken by an Earthquake not far from <hi>Locris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. Moreover one Earthquake is leſs frequent than another, and more extraordinary; one being purely miraculous, the other compounded both of Miracle and Nature.</p>
               <p n="18">18. An Earthquake meerly miraculous is, when the Earth is ſhaken by the immediate power of God, without the intervention of any Natural Cauſe.</p>
               <p>Of which ſort was that which happened at the ſuffering of Chriſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60606:9"/>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 27 51. <hi>Pliny</hi> mentions a certain great Earthquake <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 84. in the time of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar, Maximus,</hi> (ſay he) <hi>terrae memoria mortalium motus accidit Tiberii Caeſaris principatu, duodecim <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbibus Aſiae una nocte proſtratis,</hi> i. e. The greateſt Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake in the Memory of Men happened in the Reign of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> Twelve Cities of <hi>Aſia</hi> being laid level in one Night. <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Tacitus</hi> in the end of his ſecond Book, names them. But <hi>Niaphorus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. ſaies, Fourteen were deſtroyed. Saint <hi>Auſtin, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de mirabilibus. Seripturae</hi> Writes that Eleven Cities in <hi>Thrace</hi> were deſtroyed by that Earthquake, which happened at our Saviour's Crucifixion. <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports from <hi>Phlegon</hi> (an old Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) that many Houſes in the City of <hi>Niſſa,</hi> in <hi>Bithynia,</hi> fell down by the ſame Earthquake. But that Earthquake which <hi>Pleny</hi> mentions, could not be that, which happened at Chriſt's Crucifixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for they do'nt agree in the numbers of years, for thoſe Twelve Aſiatick Cities fell in the third year of <hi>Tiberius</hi>'s Reign, but Chriſt ſuffered in the 18th years of the Reign of that Emperor, or thereabouts. Moreover the ſaying of <hi>Dydimus</hi> is quoted concerning that miraculous Earthquake which was at the ſuffering of Chriſt, who ſays, <hi>Terrae Motus,</hi> &amp;c. Earthquake often happened, but thoſe which were before and after Chriſt, were only in ſome part of the Earth, but in the time of my Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, it was not ſome particular Earthquake, but the whole Earth was ſhaken and torn from its Center: But I know not what credit one may give to this Opinion of <hi>Dydimus.</hi> The Scripture ſays, the Earth is ſo founded, that he ſhall never be moved, <hi>viz.</hi> as to its Profundity and Center, Pſal. 104.5. <hi>He hath founded the Earth upon its baſis that it ſhould not be removed for ever.</hi> A paralel place, to which is in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.4.</p>
               <p>That Earthquake alſo happened at the Reſurrection of Chriſt, is to be referred to thoſe that are purely miraculous, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.2. as is alſo that ſpoken of in the 4th. of <hi>Acts</hi> 31. and that, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.26. and alſo that which happened a little before the Promulgation of the Divine Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.18. and that opening of the Earth that ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> Numb. 16.21. And that which is mentioned, <hi>Amos</hi> 1.1. and <hi>Zac.</hi> 14.5. Yea, <hi>ye ſhall flie like as you fled from before the Earthquake in the days of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah King of Judah,</hi> which, <hi>Joſephus lib.</hi> 9. <hi>antiq. cap.</hi> 2. deſcribes.</p>
               <p n="19">19. A mixt Earthquake, is that which hath a Natural cauſe, but extraordinarily, as it were increaſed by God, and in ſome ſort en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60606:9"/>beyond the Power of Nature. God often makes uſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Cauſes in the production even of miraculous Events, leſt the Agents might not be hindered without neceſſity, and that he might ſhew that the Power of Nature, and ſecond Cauſes are not at all repugnant to the Divine Power, but ſubordinate to it. And, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That he might ſhew that he hath the Power of Nature in his own hands and diſpoſal, and that he can either augment their force, or diminiſh it.</p>
               <p n="20">20. And this Earthquake is obſerved to be twofold.</p>
               <p n="21">21. One is reſtrained to ſome certain Place, and included within ſome tract of Ground, ſo that it hath an unuſual vehemency of Spirits under-ground, and wonderfully increaſed, from which ariſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and great hurt. Of which ſort was that Earthquake which happened in the 20th, or as other reckon the 22th, year of Chriſt, of which we ſpoke before, whereby 14 Cities of <hi>Aſia</hi> periſhed. Such a one was that alſo that happened in the Reign of <hi>Herod</hi> the Great, by which many Cities, Towns, and Villages being demoliſhed in <hi>Judea,</hi> 30000 <hi>Jews</hi> periſhed, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſays, in his 1ſt. Book of the Wars of the <hi>Jews, chap.</hi> 14. So from the year of Chriſt, 1170. to the year, 1345. all <hi>Germany</hi> was four times moſt grievouſly ſhaken, as one may ſee from <hi>Funccius, Stumpſius, Sigonius, Cedrenus,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Some Earthquakes are unuſual and remarkable in reſpect of their Latitude and Celerity, ſo that a great part of the World is ſhaken, and that ſome time quickly as it were, in an Hour or in a Moment. Which ſort of Earthquake Hiſtory mentions to have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the time of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperor, in the year of our Lord 369. by which the whole Earth was moved, in ſo much that many Iſlands in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> with a great multitude of Men periſhed by Inundation, which is atteſted by <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 4. Hiſt. <hi>Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 32. <hi>Amianus Marcellinus,</hi> in the end of his 26 Book. <hi>Paul Oroſius, lib.</hi> 7. Hiſt. <hi>cap.</hi> 32 <hi>Funccius</hi> in <hi>Chronol.</hi> ſo in the year of our Lord 1117. almoſt all the World ſhook, many Buildings being demoliſhed every where by it, as <hi>Stumpſius</hi> relates, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 40. but in the year 1443. an Earthquake ſhook <hi>Poland, Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia.</hi> King <hi>Ladiſtaus</hi> being not long after killed by the <hi>Turks,</hi> with a great overthrow of the Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="23">23. To this ſort of Earthquakes is referred that wonderful and unuſual one which happened in the year 1601. on the 8th of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> between one and two of the Clock at Night.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60606:10"/>
               <p n="24">24. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s not probable that ſo great a Tract of this terren Globe, as that Earthquake paſſed through, could be moved by the ordinary and accuſtomed force of Nature, which not only our <hi>European</hi> Hemiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>Germany, France, Italy, Hungary, Bohemia, Thraoe,</hi> but <hi>Aſia</hi> it ſelf is r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ported to have felt. We have not yet heard for certain l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arthq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke reached into <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> but this is certain, that the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt part of <hi>Europe</hi> trembled, and that, almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt. Some Reports have lately been hatched, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that two Towns called by the Turks <hi>Tartos</hi> and <hi>Copera,</hi> were ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> allowed up by the gaping of the Earth, cauſed by that Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at Conſternation of the Turks, who from that time belie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and unlucky Events were pretended t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their Empire, which, if true, may make it apparent, that this Earthquake was not every where a Tremor, but in ſome places a <hi>Pulſus</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: to wit, where the Spirits abound, or the Ground is porous or gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lly; as it is about the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea, and at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which City, if any in <hi>Europe,</hi> is infeſted with frequent and pernicious Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes.</p>
               <p>In the year of our Lord 1356. it was ſo grievouſly ſhaken, that a great part of the Walls<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where it looks into the Sea, fell down, with many Towers and Buildings, ſo that 13000 Men periſhed in the City, the Earthquakes laſting inceſſantly for 18 days. <hi>Agathias, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 541. relates a dreadful Earthquake that happened in this City. A little while before theſe thing happened (in the time of <hi>Juſtinian</hi>) the Earth was ſo dreadfully ſhaken at <hi>Bizantium,</hi> that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the City fell down, after which another Earthquake enſued, that was ſo great, that I think there never was, nor will be the like again.</p>
               <p n="25">25. There are therefore two things in that Earthquake which make it extraordinary and very miraculous, the breadth, and that it pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated thoſe places, which are not ſubject to Earthquakes: and the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerity of it.</p>
               <p>And although the Miſchiefs it cauſed in ſome Parts, may aſſure us ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vehemency, yet 'tis not ſo ſtupendious for its Miſchiefs, as for its Latitude, Celerity, and Preſage. For we read in Hiſtory of far more dreadful havock and deſtruction made by ſome other Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, and moreover we know from Phyſical Principles, that thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat extend fartheſt, are not ſo highly diſtruſtful. For the force of Subterraneous Spirits, the more 'tis diſſipated, the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60606:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Cauſe.</head>
               <p n="26">26. VVHether a Natural Cauſe can be aſſigned for both effects we muſt now enquire.</p>
               <p n="27">27. That there was a Natural Cauſe (although not alone) is evident from Obſervation.</p>
               <p n="28">28. For the time it ſelf is ſuch at is convenient for a Natural Earthquake, to wit, <hi>Autumn,</hi> and alſo near the <hi>Equinox,</hi> for about that time Earthquakes are wont to happen. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> 2 <hi>Meteor cap.</hi> 8. ſays, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uly Earthquakes happen chiefly in <hi>Autumn,</hi> becauſe thoſe times are moſt Windy: Which <hi>Pliny</hi> alſo relates, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="29">29. It was alſo two of the Clock in the Morning, which is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially adapted for Earthquakes. So <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the forecited place, ſays, there are more and greater Earthquakes in the Night, and adds, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, eſpecially in the Morning. And <hi>Pliny</hi> in the forecited place, ſays, the Morning and Evening Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake are very great, but at the approach of day they are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, for the heat of the day diſſolves and diſſipates their matter. Natural cold contracts and binds it.</p>
               <p n="30">30. The conſequent effects alſo do Evince that the Power of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was preſent.</p>
               <p n="31">31. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes and fragors iſſuing out of the Caverns of Earth, were heard about that time in the Neighbourhood, which is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain diſcovery of the Spirits and Winds agitated in the Cavities of the Earth, and as it were there ſtriving reciprocally. If but a little Wind blows in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o a V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſel, a ſound, and as it were, a bellowing is heard. One from whence may conclude, what happen in ſo ſpacious Caverns as thoſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth. Hence it is, that <hi>Ariſtole</hi> ſays, The <hi>Spiritus</hi> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe under the Earth, as the Air being beaten up, ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s variouſly, for there is no difference between this Spiritus and the Ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> (as to the effect of the ſound) fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus verberati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g upon every thing is it ſelf verberat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d upon: And <hi>Pliny lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 8 ſays, There goes before and accompanies them a terrible noiſe, othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wiſe a murmuring like to bellowing or the cry of Men, and the ſound fragou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of claſhing of Arms, according to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60606:11"/>the quality of the Matter receiving it, and the form either of Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uniculus through which it permeates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at Win is have ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> after an Earthquake, when a Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> has immediately p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceded it. This is alſo witneſſed by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and by <hi>Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tle</hi> and <hi>Pliny</hi> in the forecited places, that Winds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> after an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>thquak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe thoſe Winds which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in the Eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, do brake out of it into the Air. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> do aſſert the ſame concerning the Calm, to wit, that it common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y goes before an Earthquake. In a Calm towards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ays <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> there happen very many and very great Earthquakes becauſe moſt of the Matter of the Winds is ſo reſtrained in the Caverns of the Earth, that it cannot more the Air: Yet we muſt not deny that even ſometimes in windy Weather Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes have happened, becauſe all the Matter of them doth enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Caverns of the Earth together. And even at the time of our Earthquake about three hours before it was obſerved to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en, and I will not here make any tedious diſpute with <hi>Geor. Agric.</hi> who ſays, <hi>lib</hi> 4. <hi>de Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ura eorum que ef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>luant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e terra,</hi> That <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> when he mentions the darkneſs of the Sun, the calmneſs of the Weather, cold, a thin Cloud extended in length, did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to diſcover <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſigns of Earthquakes (which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters affirm) but prove by thoſe things which ſometimes happen, that W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d is the Cauſe of Earthquakes. But both may be aſſerted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſurdity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are ſigns of Earthquakes to come, and alſo evince that they are occaſioned by Wind.</p>
               <p>But h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e we do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only acknowledge Nature, but joyn with it a ſingular force of Divine Power, neither ought we to ſep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>te Divine Operations even from thoſe that are uſual and often happen: ſeeing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e very Heathens believed that there was no Earthquake, tho never ſo ſmall, but had ſomething Divine in it, as it is teſtified by <hi>Gellius lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap</hi> 28 But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s often as the Scripture ſpeaks of Earthquakes (which is often) ſo often do they divert our minds from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Nature alone, to the acknowledgment of the Omnipotent Power of the Lord, as Pſal. 60 2. <hi>Thou had made the Earth to tremble, thou had broken it,</hi> and Pſal. 77.19. Pſal. 114 4, and 7. <hi>Tremble that Earth at the preſence of the Lord, at the preſence of the God of Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> Alſo, Pſal. 10.32 <hi>He looketh on the Earth and it trembleth; he toucheth the Halls and they ſmoke,</hi> Job. 9.6. <hi>Which ſhaketh the Earth out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> place, and the Pillars thereof tremble,</hi> Nah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m 1.5. <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> quake at him, and the Hills melt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60606:11"/>
               <p n="33">33. But what ſhould be the next Natural Cauſe of ſo ſtupendious Effects, to wit, ſo great Latitude, and ſo great Celerity in this Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake? This I confeſs is difficulte to <hi>Trace,</hi> but I hope, I ſhall have leave to enquire diligently into it.</p>
               <p n="34">34. Which that I may do, I will firſt ſet down ſome Principles, where one may have good aſſurance for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Credit.</p>
               <p n="35">35 Seeing the Earth is round like a Globe, it hath Lines drawn from the Center to the Circumference.</p>
               <p n="36">36. Theſe Line meet nearer about the Center, then at the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference where they are farther diſtant.</p>
               <p n="37">37. Therefore the nearer any thing is the Center of the Earth, the mere cloſely is it contracted, raſhing violently from thence to the Circumference, 'tis extended farther, and occupi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mere r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om.</p>
               <p n="38">38. The Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pours are ſometime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more deeply hid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Center of the Earth, but ſometimes (and that more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) they are generated in Caverns and Paſſages <hi>(meatus)</hi> near<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the Superficies of the Earth.</p>
               <p>From the general Doctrine of Earthquakes in this place; I preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Earth is not otherwiſe moved then by Winds and Spirits en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred in its Cavitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, thence ſeeking an Exitus according to the quality of their Natures.</p>
               <p>I know the Ancient Philoſophers before <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> aſſigned other Cauſes of Earthquakes, whoſe different Opinions concerning them are recited by <hi>Plutarch, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>De Placitis Philoſophorum, cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Seneca lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Mat. queſt. Cap</hi> 4. <hi>Pliny lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 79. but eſpecially, <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> 2 <hi>Meteor, cap.</hi> 7. But amongſt modern Authors <hi>Joannes Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeus, Picus Mirandula, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>examinis doctinae &amp; vanitatis gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, cap.</hi> 12. among which we muſt reckon <hi>Nicholaus Cuſanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> who <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Docta ignorantia,</hi> is of opinion, that the Earth is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of an Oval form, nor altogether Unmovable of it ſelf. But no Opinion is more evident from Nature and Experience, than <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> who aſſerts, that Winds and ſubterraneous Spirits are the Cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Earthquakes; for the heavieſt Bodies are only to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by that which hath the ſtrongeſt Power to move; But among all inferiour Beings, the Wind or Spiritus is that which according to the qualifications of its own Nature, hath in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Power more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective of Motion than any other body <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is expreſly teſtified by Holy Writs, when it aſſimilates Angels to the Winds, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.7. and many experiments do al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o evince it: For with how great a force doth a little G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n-Powd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60606:12"/>into Spirits by the heat of Fire burſt out of the ſmalleſt Machines. So we ſee the Spirit of new Wine when ſeething, if the Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nell be ſtoped, do penetrate the Veſſels, that they may break <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orth It is ſufficiently known of what Power they are in our Bodies, and what great Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, Symp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, and Pains they are the cauſes of. So that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> uſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Example chiefly to confirm his Opinion of the Cauſe of Earthquake.</p>
               <p n="39">39. Theſe Spirits being deep in the Earth and cloſeley contracted, the nearer they arrive a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Superficies of the Earth, the more they are diſſipated and ſcattered, and ſo they ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end further in length and breadth.</p>
               <p n="40">40. And they more powerfully endeavour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o extri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e themſelves; and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, by now much he more they are deeply laid in the Earth, and cloſely contracted.</p>
               <p>Which may be proved by he experiment of Fire, which when it is narrowly contracted, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaks for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e more violently man inſtant, when it hath the opor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity of in A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, which is apparent in Gun, where the ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ou force of the Gun-Powder being ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in a nerrow room, breaks out ſwifter than one can think or imagin.</p>
               <p n="41">41. Which Principles being preſuppoſed, let us now ſhew the Cauſe of the Earthquake which we are treating of, which extended ſo far, and was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o quickly cauſed.</p>
               <p n="42">42. It was a Vapour or Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubtilly diſpoſed and bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundly toward the Center of the Earth or at leaſt the Center of <hi>Europe,</hi> or of thoſe Countries that were ſhaken, whence ſallying out in great quantity and number, it ſpread fare and near with wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Celerity.</p>
               <p>Trembling in the Earth is nothing elſe but the Thunder in a Cloud, ſays <hi>Pliny, lib</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 79. As therefore ſome Thunder reache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and iſſues out more violently than other, both according to the different diſpoſition of the Cloud, and alſo according to the quantity and quality of the Spirit deeply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ried in the Cloud, or approaching nearer to its Superficies; ſo the greater or leſſer Latitude and Celerity of Earthquakes, is to be derived from the different diſpoſition and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ituation of the Spirits. And that alſo, which we aſſerted of the Center, is eaſie to be underſtood: For that which is placed in the middle of a Circle or Globe, doth more eaſily move the whole Globe, than that which recedes from the Center towards the ſide of the Globe; which is well known by them who prepare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60606:12"/>Fireballs, and throw them into the Air, often to the great Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spectators. And I call that the Center of <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ope,</hi> which is in the midſt of that Circle which is drawn from one Extream o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ope</hi> to the other, in that ſpace of the Terrene Goble in which <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ope</hi> is contained.</p>
               <p n="43">43. But whence comes it, that this Spirit is ſo deep, ſo ſubtil, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wiſt? Partly from the firſt, and partly from the ſecond Cauſes.</p>
               <p n="44">44. The efficacy of Celeſtical Bodies doth d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rvedly claim the firſt place among ſecond Cauſes, which riſes from their different reſpect to one another, or the mixture of their li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht and rays. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower of the Subject as is it ſelf, ſeeing therefore Heaven is the firſt, che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, greateſt, and ſwifteſt of all Bodies, its Force and Efficacy muſt need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be the firſt, greateſt and ſwifteſt; for Heaven is ſo cloſely connexed with inferiour Bodies, that its virtue may be tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d into the Earth and communicated to it, even in its moſt abſtruſe rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es: Whither he efficacy of the ſolar Rays doth reach, is evident from the generation of Metals and other ſubterraneous Bodies, which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no ways poſſible without the Sun and its Rays.</p>
               <p n="45">45 The efficay and vertue of <hi>Saturn</hi> this very year was chefieſt amongſt the Planets, whence it happened that Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter and Fuel was afforded for cold Vapours both above and within the Earth.</p>
               <p>'Tis an Aſtronomical Rule confirmed by experience, that the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Earthquake is to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved from <hi>Saturn,</hi> it being a Planet effective of cold and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s; And the firſt matter of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours is cold and dry, which being gathered together at firſt, by the intervention of other Cauſes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s hot an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is rar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied.</p>
               <p>To which may be added the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rate Aſpect of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> in <hi>July,</hi> whereby cold Vapours are made hot and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for windy Temperament. 'Tis an old Opinion confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Reaſons drawn from the Nature and Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets; and alſo from experience, that the Power of the three Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our Planets, <hi>Saturn, Jupiter,</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s moſt eminent in producing Earthquakes; the firſt by his light doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncreaſe cold Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, which are made hot by the third, and ſo tempered by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, that the heat being neither able to ſubdue, nor b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubdued, there are neceſſarily generated flatuous Vapours, whereof we ſhall ſpeak hereafter.</p>
               <p n="47">47 And when the Earthquake happened, the Sun was in the Sign of <hi>Virgo,</hi> which is it ſelf very much ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pted for Earthquake.</p>
               <p n="48">48. There happened in the foregoing Month of <hi>July</hi> two Eclipſes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60606:13"/>the Moon on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un's on the Nineteenth, and no wonder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me divers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s were coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed within the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> being weakned by their being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſing from ram, could not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> all which, the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eting of two Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one Month <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ging Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</p>
               <p>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the Eclipſes of the Sun and the Moo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2 <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p</hi> 8 and of <hi>Pliny</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is confirmed by ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ene rat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the heat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es by a certain Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, are purged fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is which can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot be when thoſe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ts are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umouts abound, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſo the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would otherwiſe op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhut up, ſo that he Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s cannot regularly and convenientl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exhale: So ſays <hi>Ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or cap</hi> S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>thqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes happen abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clipſes for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the defect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ceſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat, which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by the Sun or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on throughout the Air. Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>her do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h that A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> want its Found<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on; many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mencies enſue to the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld upon the Obſcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aries of Heaven in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nth. I don't ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re of that eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es which is in <hi>Potentia</hi> and hath its reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd to futurities, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of that which is in <hi>Actu</hi> and accompanies an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clipſe con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dered in it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="49">49. To which may be added that which is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earer Cauſe, to wit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Conſtitut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of the Air, which in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c din<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Summer was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>apted for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ration of flatuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Vapours.</p>
               <p n="50">50. Abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beginning of Summer, there was very hot Weather, by which the Faith was prep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red and diſpoſed to engender and receive Vapou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</p>
               <p n="51">51. Which was foll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wed in the midſt of Summer by continual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by which the Earth being opened b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore, by the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deeply w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tted, that abundance of Humours muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſarily have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ored up.</p>
               <p>Which c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, is atteſted by <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtotle</hi> in the afor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaid place, 2. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(ſays he)</hi> happen in <hi>Spring</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iny Weather, becauſe then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haltation, which being in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rcepted in the nar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> paſſages of the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, is there th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t in; becauſe the Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties of the Earth are full, but when the Wind in contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hin a narrow place, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ive of Mot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. And there is a remark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60606:13"/>place in the beginning of the Chapter, where he ſays, that the Earth is of it ſelf dry, yet, but reaſon of ſhowers fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t hath likewiſe much moiſture which proceeds from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re which is in it ſelf, and engenders much Spirits both wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hin and without it ſelf Neither is there any reaſon why any one ſhould ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>Seneca</hi> ſays, <hi>in qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> That no rain is ſo great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to or We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Earth above two Foot: For that is not true of ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhower of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain, nor of much and continued rain, neither in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Earth, the only conveyance of rain into the Earth, but it alſo is carried through the Caves of the Earth that are open and is in great pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ry infu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d into the in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Receſſes of the Earth, by Fountains, Wells, and Rivers which are increaſed by rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="52">52. To which rainy Weather was added an unuſual co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in the <hi>Dog Days,</hi> by which the Paſſages and Pores of it were ſo ſhut up, that the Humours gathered together in the Earth could not evaporat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="53">53. And the <hi>South Weſt</hi> wind blowed for many days together, ſo that the Vapours accommodated for an E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rthquake were en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d and nouriſhed. For the <hi>South Wind</hi> is warm and moiſt, ſo that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath been rightly obſerved by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that it is apt both to excite and nouriſh the matter that cauſes an Earthquake; and as the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>outh-Weſt</hi> Wind is near in place, ſo in temper and effect.</p>
               <p n="54">54. Which cold Weather was preſently followed by a ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mneſs and heat a little before the end of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> So that the Vapo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s which had been generated by continual Rain within the Cave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns of the Earth, grew dry: And a Vapour made warm b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>es a ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous. And when there ariſe ſuch contention between cold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or and heat, in which the cold is neither q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite overcome and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, nor the heat is altogether conqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, winds are eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed. Which is rightly obſerved by Phyſicians in the Bodies of Men, when he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t acting up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Phleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n cannot totally conſume it, then are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds.</p>
               <p n="55">55. It could not be but that the Vapours contracted within the Earth by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppoſing cold, both proper to the Earth, and alſo cauſed by the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>al Conſtitution of the Air, ſhould be deeply laid. No otherwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an it the Spirits are more deeply concealed and conſtrain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, when the coldneſs of the Clouds doth reſiſt and conſtrain more ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iffly.</p>
               <p n="56">56. The ſubterraneous Fire ſcattered through the Cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Earth, ſo heated theſe Vapours ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t up in the Earth very deeply, that it made them more ſubtil and more a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the Caverns
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60606:14"/>thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh <hi>Europe</hi> and other places being diſpoſed for it, for the Reaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>That there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire every where ſcattered through the Cavities of the Earth, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h the Fire which in many places breake forth out of the moſt pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>found C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves of the Earth doth evince, as alſo the hot Waters or Baths which riſe in many places, to add nothing of the engend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>phur, Brimſtone, and other Minerals, in which there is an igneous force and nature. The burning of <hi>Aetna</hi> equally celebrated by Peers and G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ographers, is deſcribed by <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p.</hi> 2 <hi>Heny,</hi> the Nephew of that <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> by his Siſter whoſe death the <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſuvian</hi> Mountain cauſed, ſay, <hi>lib.</hi> 2 <hi>Epict.</hi> 
                  <q>Not long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the Iſland <hi>Georgia</hi> (one of thoſe iſles they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll the Third) ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a dreadful Earthq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake and gap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d out ſome much F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ame, ſo many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot Stores, ſo much Sulph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r and burning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rimſtones which were t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rown into the Air that many Houſes were Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt, Inhabitants deſtroyed, Vine-yards and Gardens quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feced.</q> But whence come ſo many Flames under the Earth? From the dry Vapours which being ſo cloſely preſs'd in the Earth, and from ſeveral motions and agitattions in it, Fire doth neceſſarily Kindle: For Fire, ſays <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed ſmoke. About the year 1541 Fire broke out of a fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tain named <hi>Eliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um. Gregor. Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cola d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſquae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uunt è terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 152. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <hi>Stra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> Writes, that ſo great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re iſſued out of the Earth, that ſome Towns were conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and among th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dom</hi> at the Lake <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>phaltites:</hi> But we are t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ught better by <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes</hi> in his ſacred Hiſtory. Moreover as our Fire wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 'tis ſhut in, is moved up and down by a various Reciprocation, ſome doubt not bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire is diverſly excited, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſlies downwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto the moſt profound Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, towards the higheſt Parts of the Earth, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth is variouſly changed and diſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by Heaven and the Air.</p>
               <p n="57">57 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe I take to be the ſecond Cauſes of that Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it which lately ſhoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Earth ſo ſwiftly and ſo deeply, which yet could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly produce to unuſual an Earthquake, by its Natural Power alone.</p>
               <p n="58">58. To which was added that chief and firſt Cauſe, God, who by an extraordinary way of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing, wonderfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſed the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th of that Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed within the Earth, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> added one d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of force to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ond its own Power, which N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ture c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld no add, ſo that this Earthquake may be recko<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed not purely Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ural, but mixt with both, as we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erted before. For ad Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60606:14"/>do not exclude N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ture, but many include it, ſo that they increaſe its force and vertue, and ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd it to that degree, to which it could not attain unleſs the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y Pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> were ſuperadded. The Scripture doth prepoſe u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n evident E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of it in <hi>Sampſon,</hi> whoſe predigious ſtrength by his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ddy Temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, and all his Sinews and Muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les were ſo exceedingly ſtreng. However God himſelf did reinforce and increaſe them ſo much that be could rent into pieces a young roaring Lion like a Kid, <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.7. that he could break the ſtrongeſt Cords like a Linnen-thread or Flax; that he could ſlay a Thouſand Men, with the Jaw of an <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Judg.</hi> 15. That he could take the Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs of the Gates of the City, and the two Poſts, and carry them upon his Shoulders to the tep of an Hill, <hi>Judg.</hi> 16. So the Divine Power of God did increaſe the natural ſtrength of <hi>David,</hi> that he could overthrew this prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and <hi>Stronglined body Goliah</hi> with a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing only. 1 <hi>San<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ud</hi> 17. To the ſame kind of Miracle we may refer the Example of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lijah.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. where it is ſaid, that having eat a Cake and drank Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of a Cruiſe, he was ſo ſuſtained, that in the ſtrength of that Meat he went forty days and forty nights unto <hi>Hereb, the Mount of God.</hi> There are evidences enough throughout all the Doctrines of Divines concerning the variety of Miracles, their many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orts and their ends to ſhew that theſe ſtrengthning and reinforcing of Natural Faculties, though ſupplied by God; may fall out alſo on err Ages, as we have obſerved in a few words before in the nineteenth <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Effects and Preſages.</head>
               <p n="59">59. ALthough thoſe things which happen contrary to Nature, have not an end properly and perſe out of Nature, yet they have their effects preſages, and portenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, When Earthquake happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides its Nature, it cannot have an end properly, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the Earth. For the end of every thing is according to its
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60606:15"/>Nature, 2. <hi>Phyſ.</hi> 3. But in reſpect of the Vapours or Spiritus by which the Earth is moved, this end is aſſigned by Naturaliſts, that the nature of that Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itus may be preſerved whilſt ſallying out of the Earth, it aſcends into the open Air, making its own way out of the Caverns o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Earth, in which it was included as in its Priſon, ſo g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning a place proper and agreablee to its own Nature.</p>
               <p n="60">60. And ſeeing this Earthquake is mixed with Nature and Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, it hath Natural effects, and alſo its preſages from the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Ordination of God.</p>
               <p n="61">61. The effects will be as is the Cauſe, to wit, Praeternatural, that is contrary to Nature.</p>
               <p n="62">62. Three of which effects are more eſpecially to be feared, which both the Nature of Earthquakes, and Experience, and the Obſervation of Examples do evince, to wit, Sickneſs, Inundations, and Sterility.</p>
               <p n="63">63. Earthquakes cauſe Epidemical and Contagious Diſtempers, becauſe the Vapours in the Caverns of the Earth either contract rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs or ſome venemous qualities (eſpecially if ſhut up in it for any conſiderable time) and thence ſallying out, they make impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the Air that ſurrounds us, which when drawn into our Bodies by breathing, there muſt needs be impreſſed the like qualities in the inmoſt Bowels of our Bodies; Neither do they only infect the Air, but alſo the Water without which we cannot be. That the quality of ſubterraneous Vapours is very prejudiciable to our Health, is teſtified by experience in thoſe places where the Earth abounding with Minerals, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds into the Air frequent Exhalations, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if the Earth be porous and looſe. Neither need we go very far for Examples: Thoſe Caverns which are at the Sharp, and the Fountains of <hi>Schwalbuh</hi> may teſtifie it, which are ſo much infeſted with venemous Exhaltations, that Dogs or Hens carried into them, die ſooner than any one can imagine. <hi>Geor. Agric.</hi> hath Writ ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de nat. rer. è terra effluent.</hi> When at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Book he Writes, the Air which is ſhut up a long time in any Concavity of the Earth, rots and is made peſtilent: And a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te after; there are in many places of the Earth ſerobes, exhaling mortiferous Vapours, but no where more then in <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> alſo in the Appendix of his Work <hi>de Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um varietate,</hi> explains the thing by ſome Hiſtories and Examples. Moreover the Hiſtory of all Times teacheth us what grievous and peſtilent Diſtempers have been cauſed by Earthquakes. <hi>Seneca lib.</hi> 6. <hi>quoeſt. natu.</hi> atteſts that a Flock of 600 Sheep was deſtroyed by an Earthquake in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60606:15"/>the Province called <hi>Pompeia.</hi> Sheep being of a very ſoft nature and carry their heads near the Ground. In the 19th. years from the building of <hi>Rome,</hi> after an Earthquake, followed a Plague, which laſting three years, there died at <hi>Rome</hi> 30000 men. So in the year of our Lord 748. after an Earthquake in <hi>Paleſtine</hi> a great Sickneſs was prevalent in <hi>Sicily, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Thrace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the year 801. when <hi>Charles</hi> the Great was inveſted with the Empire, Upper <hi>Germany</hi> was infeſted with a vehement Earthquake, but eſpecially the Coaſt of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> which was followed by a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, which dreadfully afflicted <hi>Germany</hi> and other Places. <hi>Stump. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. So in the year 1309. on the Feaſt of the Converſion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> all <hi>Germany</hi> ſhook, and the Plague afterwards raged throughout the Country, ſo that 60000 men are reported to have died at <hi>Florence</hi> and 90000 at <hi>Lubeck.</hi> That God the Father of all Mercy would grant, that no ſuch conſequence may happen from our late Earthquake, and that the Epidemical Diſeaſe which now infeſt theſe Places, ſo near to a kind of a putrid and malignant Feaver may not be converted into a more dangerous Diſtemper. The unlucky Eclipſes and Poſitions of the heavenly Bodies this years portend ſome ſuch things in other Countries. The <hi>Northern</hi> Latitude of <hi>Saturn</hi> in the Sign of <hi>Scorpius;</hi> and thoſe four Eclipſes of the foregoing year, two of which happened in the Month of <hi>June,</hi> whereof that of the Sun was a ſtupendious one for its Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, will exert their Operations this year as the Maſters do reckon.</p>
               <p>But that the Waters are alſo polluted by thoſe Vapours is known by the Fountains, which both before and after Earthquakes are wont to be impurer and thicker. Which is alſo atteſted by <hi>Pliny, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 81. where, <hi>he ſays,</hi> The Water in Wells is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cker and not without a loath ſome ſmell, which odour is Sulphu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and metalline, from whence one may certainly conclude that ſome Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours ſallying out of the Earth, have mingled themſelves with the Water. Hence it is, that <hi>Pherecydes Pythagoras</hi> his Maſter foretold an Earthquake by drawing ſome Water out of a Well, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which <hi>Pliny</hi> Writes, as by ſome Divine Preſage, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 29. Which <hi>Cicero</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntions 1. <hi>de Divinat. Geor. Agricol. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de efflu. è terr. pag.</hi> 153. think that muddy Water in Wells is moſt commonly a Sign of an Earthquake already begun, and he believes that no proper and certain Sign of future Earthquake can be aſſigned, for thoſe that are delivered by Writers are either the Sign of an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60606:16"/>Earthquake juſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, or its Modas; ſo that they may happen w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ho <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> future Earthquake.</p>
               <p n="64">64. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Earch are therefore wont to enſue Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>olently ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lying out of the Earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Caverns wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eous Waters are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Water is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more abound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> manner driven into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Fountains and R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vers.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>le,</hi> 2. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. cap.</hi> 8. Exhalations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with great Force, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y along with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whatſoever Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ds in the ſame place, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Wills that blow the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ary way are the Cauſe of it, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th,</hi> it cannot repel the Sea brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t it by another Wind Examples alſo obſerved in Hiſtory, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. For <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de bello Gothor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, pag.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ribes the unuſual In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as ariſing from an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake. About <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Earthquake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ppe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed which ſhook <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia</hi> and the other places, about the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nas G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> number of other places and levelled ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht Citi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth Ground. And the Earth in ſome places when it had gaped <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> again to its former ſtate, but in other places <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo much cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, that the People of that Country were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a large Circuit to converte with one another. But in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sea between <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aly</hi> and <hi>Beotia</hi> there aroſe ſo great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo great an in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndation, that great deſolation was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>atai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ices, and Men. In the ſee and year <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Flev. Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam</hi> and <hi>Vale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> the Sea to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>led that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erflowing <hi>Sicily,</hi> it Buried in its Waves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>nal Towas and V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. In the year 1508. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Earthquake was ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dation; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>out all <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany.</hi> And wiſh we might take example and experiment of that calam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the late Earthquake, that we mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be brought to repenta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>In the ſame place 'tis ſad, <q>We have ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s daily of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ous Inundations through the Butchy of <hi>Juliers</hi> and <hi>Clav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> and the Oriental <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iezla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d.</hi>
                  </q> We have been eye Witneſſes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>creaſing of the River <hi>Neker,</hi> which overflowed in <hi>December</hi> and <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> with a conſiderable damage.</p>
               <p>How the <hi>Rome</hi> hath overſloved, the Inhabitants know to their own forrow and loſs, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at unuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Inundation proceeding from the River and Rivulets in <hi>December,</hi> between <hi>Strab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ang</hi> and <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> as it was fard to ſeveral perſons, ſo among the reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the head of an Ancient Family.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60606:16"/>
               <p n="65">65. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Barrenneſs is the conſequent of an Earthquake becauſe of the envenomed Vapoars which while they p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace the pores of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>arth, leave behind them their Venemou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Footſteps, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Qualiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> both on the Earth it ſelf, and alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the enlivening Power ſit for the production of Corn is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Wonderful and different were the Sentiments of the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> People after the late Earthquake, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is uſual; and Husband <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> every where heard interpreting this Earthquake as a Joyful O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a ſingular future Fertili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y. But this Conjecture is eaſily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſuted by the conſideration of Natural Cauſes, eſpecially ſince Hiſtory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the contrary. For in the Year 315. from the building of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo great a Scarcity and Barrenneſs ſo lowed an Earthquake, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> mentions it as remarkable that many threw themſelves into <hi>Tiber,</hi> where they made at one another to devour themſelves. In the Year of our Lord 542 an univerſal and moſt grievous Famine enſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d upon an Earthquake, that was it ſelf almoſt univerſal, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Paul Diaco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, lib.</hi> 16. The ſame happened in the Year 1326. and again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But as Plagu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Inundation do not follow a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Earthquake <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo neither do B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s and Fam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne: For as the Subterrancous Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are not alway; equally diſpoſed, ſo ſometimes they are leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>omed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and more ſubtil, that they ethale ſooner, neither do they ſo eaſily imprint on the Ground any quality no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en that we may experience in this Earthquake the next. Harveſt, let him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one who is able to crown the Year with his B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing gram.</p>
               <p n="66">66. And a this Earthquake was not only natural, but or kind to a miraculous one, ſo alſo ſee us to contain in it the Preſages and Porten a of ſome wonderful and extraordinary Change; among Mankind I ſaid before that God add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a Supernatural for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and degres o the Natural Cauſes of this Earthquake. And God doth nothing in vain, but direct all to ſome certain end and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo that 'tis neceſſary ſomething ſhould be in this Earthquake more than could proceed from the power of Nature alone.</p>
               <p n="67">67. But as Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nets do not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves and their own nature cauſe or denounce any Change in Kingdoms, and any other Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo neither do Earthquakes; but ſuch events hap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a in theſe wonderful and ſecret Works of Nature from the diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d and Ordinations of God, partly exciting Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Minds and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng them, partly terrifying them with thoſe ſear of Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. The Rainbow of its own Nature can neither be a ſurety for, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60606:17"/>the Grace and Covenant of God to the World, that there ſhall be no more an univerſal Flood, but it doth engage for, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it by a ſupernatural Revelation, which the gracious Counſel of God impoſed on this work of Nature. The ſame muſt be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined of Earthquakes, Comets, Chaſins and other wonderful Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors in Nature.</p>
               <p n="68">68. But what change in <hi>Europe</hi> doth this Earthquake preſage? This neither I nor any body elſe can eaſily tell. He alone knows who endowed the Earthquake with the ſignification of Futurities, who encreaſed and augmented the Power of Nature; and laſtly who hath at his own diſpoſe, both the Cauſes and their Effects.</p>
               <p n="69">69. The Scripture, as far I could obſerve, ſpeaks of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes after a three fold manner.</p>
               <p n="70">70. Sometimes as of the Sign and Symbol of the preſent Grace of God already held forth. As was that Earthquake by which the Apoſtles and other Members of the Primitive Church were confirmed againſt the intermediate Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aults of their Enemies, by the hearing and the preſence of God from Heaven, of which <hi>Acts</hi> 4. v. 31. <hi>But when they had prayed,</hi> ſays <hi>Luke, the place in which they were Aſſenbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d was ſhaken, and they were all filled with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> To which is to be referred that Earthquake that happened at the Reſurrection of Chriſt, the Angel of the Lord deſcending from Heaven, and Rowling away the Stone from the mouth of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, of which, <hi>Matt. cap.</hi> 98. verſ. 2. makes mention. To the number of theſe Earthquakes doth alſo belong that which is mentioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. <hi>But in the middle of the night,</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>were Fraying and Singing of Pſalm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, when on a ſudden there was a great Earthquake, ſo that the Foundations of the Priſon were ſhaken, and the Doors were oppened, and all their bonds were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="71">71. But as ſuch Earthquakes are ſoldom, ſo they are meerly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: and ſuch Examples are not eaſily to be found either in the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tory of our own or former Times: For the Sins of Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rwiſe.</p>
               <p n="72">72. But the Scripture often ſpeaks of an Earthquake as of the Meſſenger and Witneſs of the Divine Wrath, and the preſage of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to certain Kingdoms and Provinces for the Publick and Private Sins of the eminent Ones. The Scripture ſcarcely over ſpeaks more frequently of any preſage of the Wrath of God and in pending Puniſhments, than of an Earthquake, as the <hi>2d.</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60606:17"/>
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. verſ. 8. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 18. verſ. 8. <hi>The Earth is ſhaken and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, becauſe his Wrath is Kindled.</hi> Job 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>Who remove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mountains, ſo as he is not obſerved; who overturns them in his Wrath, who moves the Earth out of its place; So that the Pillars thereof ſhake.</hi> So Eccleſ. 39 32. <hi>There are Winds created for puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhment, in the conſummated time they pour out the ſtrength and fury of him that made them.</hi> And the like places in <hi>Joel</hi> 2.1. <hi>Na.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Amos</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Zac.</hi> 14. <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.21. And God was pleaſed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgate his Laws by an Earthquake, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.18. That he might teſtifie that, that puniſhment was ready for the breakers of them. To which muſt be referr'd that Earthquake which happened whilſt Chriſt ſuffered, <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.51. <hi>The Earth,</hi> ſays he, <hi>was moved, and the Rocks were ſplit; which was alſo a Teſtimony of Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Innocence. John</hi> in the <hi>Revela.</hi> denouncing the Wrath of God and the puniſhments which are to be poured forth on the later days, makes often mention of an Earthquake, <hi>cap.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.13. <hi>There was,</hi> ſays he, <hi>in that hour a great Earthquake, and the tenth part of the World fell, and there were kill'd in the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> 7000 <hi>men, and the reſt was terrified and gave Glory to the God of Heaven.</hi> cap. 16.18. <hi>There was a great Earthquake, ſuch as never was ſince Men were on the Earth, an Earthquake,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſo great.</hi> Which ſayings although they have an Allegorical inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, yet they may be taken properly; or at leaſt they will lead us to this, that the Scripture doth commonly repreſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructful puniſhments and calamities by an Earthquake.</p>
               <p n="73">73. For nothing ſeems to be a greater puniſhment and calamity to Mankind, than an Earthquake.</p>
               <p n="74">74. For all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her fatal puniſhments are wont to enſue upon an Earthquake, and we may ſooner foreſee War, Famine, and Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and ſo take heed of, and avoid them by preparing proper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, than we can foreſee avoid and fly from an Earthquake: ſeeing the Spiritus in the Earth is not reſtrained by any Humane force, neither can we fly away from the Earth. Hence it is that Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce witneſſeth, that Brute Beaſts and Men are terrified by nothing ſo much as by an Earthquakes; ſo we ſee that even the moſt ſavage and cruel Hearts of Tyrants, that have their minds hardened moſt againſt God and Men, have been terrified by Earthquakes. There is extant in <hi>Joſephus,</hi> a memorable paſſage concerning this, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de bell. Jud. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>and lib.</hi> 15. <hi>Autiq. Jud.</hi> Where <hi>Herod</hi> a deſpiſer of God and Men, thus Speaks to his Army. <hi>Let not the Fear of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60606:18"/>inanimate things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all terrifie you, nor imagine that Earthquake is an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of future diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ctio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; for the defects of the Elements themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Natural, and infor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o other loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> than, that which they cauſe; ſo that when they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>happen, they are inded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y their own greatneſs.</hi> Theſe Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne Speeches did the Tyrant then utter, whilſt he himſelf was ſo aſtoniſhed in his own Mind, that he offered Sacrifice for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing of God, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> mentions in the ſame place. The Heath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s being always terrined by Earthquakes, began then in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to think of appeaſing God, and rightly of inſtituting their Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. Hence it is, that <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. For there is not only in an Earthquake ſome ſimple evil and danger, but an equal or greater Omen of ſomething to come. The City of <hi>Rome</hi> never t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mbled (yet it ſhook in the year 537. about fifty ſeven times) but it was the Omen of ſome future Event. Therefore that impious ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Seneca</hi> is repugnant to the Senſe and Conſcience of Mankind. The God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do nothing of theſe thing, neither is the Heaven or the Earth ſhaken by the anger of the Deities. So <hi>Gellius, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 28. What is the Cauſe of Earthquake, is not yet manifeſt: Therefore the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cient <hi>Romans,</hi> when they either perceived or were told that the Earth ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook, commanded by their Edits that Holydays ſhould be kept, but in the publiſhing of them did not name the God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s uſual, for whom the ſame were to be kept, and <hi>Marcus Varro,</hi> ſays, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>was ſo obſerved by the Decide of the Prieſts, becauſe 'twas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain whether the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rth trembled by the Power of the Gods or Goddeſſes. There is ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt in <hi>Roſinus,</hi> the Hiſtory of ſome Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious expiation, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6 where he ſays, <hi>That grievous La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>es enſued upon the Death of</hi> Valentinian. <hi>Crete</hi> was vehemently ſhaken with all <hi>Peloponneſus</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Greece,</hi> except <hi>Athens</hi> and the Country thereof, which they ſay, was ſaved by this means. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtorius</hi> the High Prieſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w in a Dream the <hi>Athenians</hi> advis'd to prefer the Hero <hi>Achilles</hi> to the higheſt Honnours, for this would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt advantagious; he therefore being taught by Divine Speculations, after having performed a ſolemn Sacrifice, placed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> under <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>'s, ſo was <hi>Athen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll its Lard ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e from the Earthquake. There is a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>lled place in <hi>Syneſius Cyre. Epiſ.</hi> 61. of Devotion in the time of Earthquakes. God often (<hi>ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he</hi> 
                  <q>cauſed an Earthquake in the day time, and Men ſtood commonly upright whiſt they pray'd, for the Ground w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſhaken wherefore thinking the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> more ſeverely ſhaker th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the Land, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>an to the Heaven, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q> Chriſtian of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>ive Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d not to fly to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60606:18"/>any unkown God, but to the true one that ſhake; the Earth and implored his Grace and Mercy; an Example of which pious Cuſtom is related by <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the Emperour, who when he heard that <hi>Antiochia</hi> was ſhaken by a grievous Earthquake, in which a great number of Men had periſhed, preſently laid down his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem and Imperial Robes, and put Sackcloth, and publiſhed an Edict whereby he commanded his ſubjects to Faſt and Pray for many days, and to do all other things, which teſtifie a ſerious repentance. <hi>Sozomenus, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Stump, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>There is extant alſo an Epiſtle of <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antoninus</hi> to the People of <hi>Aſia,</hi> wherein he exhorts them not to lay the Fault of the Earthquake upon the Chriſtians, but rather religiouſly to invoke after their faſhion the Author of the Earthquake; <q>It will not be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, continues he, to comfort your ſorrow by a juſt warning, for I have found out that in ſuch occaſions you do aſcribe theſe ordinary Events to ſome motive of envy, that the God, whom they truſt much to, may have; and whilſt that you know not the Reaſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, you do neglect every time the Worſhip of the other Gods, and ſo you endeavour to put away and caſt down the Worſhip of the immortal God, whom the Chriſtians do adore.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And there is no doubt but that many pious Men every where through <hi>Germany</hi> and other Countrys, devoutly and religiouſly followed that pious Cuſtom of the Ancient Church, and ſtirr'd up themſelves to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Repentance and ardent invoking of God's name: which effect if it hath not happened in all, yet the thoughts of the Evils which have in all Ages enſued upon the Earthquakes, ought ſtill to ſtir them up and awaken them to true repentance, ſeeing thoſe effects have been obſerved by the moſt ſevere Writers of Earthquakes. For it is not raſh to ſay that commotions of the mind follow an Earthquake, as a Shadow the Body. Neither does it want its natural Cauſes, for 'tis certain that the Air we draw in, have ſeveral change of altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by Earthquakes, and the Temperament, and ſo the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nners of Men are much affected with the temperateneſs or intemperatneſs of the Air, and they are diſpoſed by it, if we believe the moſt kilful Phyſitians, and our own experience. Hiſtories are full of Examples, of which I will inſtance but one or two. <hi>Delus</hi> trembled about the time of the <hi>Peloponneſian</hi> War (which was called immoveable by <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> relate out of <hi>Calliſthenes, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Nat. quaeſt.</hi>) Whilſt <hi>Brenno</hi> was attacking the <hi>Del-phian</hi> Temple, there happened ſo great an Earthquake, and ſo great a Tempeſt mingled with Hail and Rain,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60606:19"/>that the <hi>Gaulois</hi> Army were almoſt overwhelmed. Earthquakes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened often in the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> War, ſo that 'twas ſaid at <hi>Rome,</hi> an Earthquake happened 57 times in the ſame year, in which the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Carthagians</hi> fighting at the Lake <hi>Traſimenian,</hi> were neither of them ſenſible of a great Earthquake which was there, <hi>Flin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4 and in the 83. he ſays, <hi>That two Mountains ran againſt one another, riſing and retiring with a great noiſe, by which concourſe all the Towns were daſh'd to peices and Cattle between kill'd,</hi> which was in the year before the <hi>Social</hi> War, and ſays he, <hi>I know not but it may be more fatal to</hi> Italy, <hi>than the War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the year of our Lord 369. many Earthquakes happened every where which where followed by a moſt ſevere Perſecution under the Emperour <hi>Valantinian,</hi> as is atteſted by <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Euſebius.</hi> In the year 455. a remarkable Earthquake preceded thoſe dreadful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſtations of the Country of <hi>Attila,</hi> as is Witneſſed among others by <hi>Stump: lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 54. So in the year 841. <hi>Herbipolis</hi> ſhook about twenty times, upon which a bloody War enſued between the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Lotharin,</hi> and his Brother. So in the year 1171. a War broke out between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Sweedes,</hi> when ſeveral Earthquakes had preceded it every where through <hi>Germany.</hi> So in the ſame year 1171. a great War aroſe between the Emperour <hi>Friderick</hi> the I. and Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the III. In the year 1372. on the firſt of <hi>June,</hi> a dreadful Earthquake ſhook <hi>Germany,</hi> and a little after enſued a grievous War in <hi>Bavaria</hi> and <hi>Sweedland.</hi> Alſo in the year 1384. on <hi>Chriſtmas</hi>'s-<hi>Eve,</hi> the Earthquake ſhook, and a little after enſued the dreadful War of <hi>Leopol</hi> with the <hi>Switzers,</hi> which was both deſtruction to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and fatal to the Young Prince <hi>Leopold.</hi> In the ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r 1521. before <hi>Belgrade</hi> was taken by the <hi>Turks,</hi> the Neighbourhood ſhook for 3 days together, and many Houſes fell down every where. I cannot but ſet down the Words of a wiſe old Man, <hi>Gaſpar Peucer,</hi> which are extant in his Commentary of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinations, <hi>pag.</hi> 389. <q>The Mountains of <hi>Suda</hi> and the Towns built there felt: Not only one or two, but continual ſhakings of the Earth (which ſays Hiſtory always denounce great Wars and deſtructive Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions) the Houſes ſhaking as if it proceeded from the diſtinct im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of Winds.</q> Theſe things undoubtedly threaten dreadful deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and calamities, which I pray God mercifully mitigate for the ſake of his Church, and ſpare the innocent and guiltleſs Ages for the ſake of his Eternal Son Jeſus Chriſt. But there is another Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple freſher in our Memory, <hi>viz.</hi> of the year 1590. when ſome parts
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60606:19"/>of <hi>Germany,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Auſtria, Bavaria,</hi> and <hi>Miſnia</hi> were ſhaken, which Earthquake is the more remarkable and worthy to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the late one, becauſe it happened almoſt at the ſame time, <hi>viz.</hi> on 5th. of <hi>September,</hi> and becauſe a litte after the <hi>Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh</hi> War grew more outragious in <hi>Hungary.</hi> And laſtly, becauſe a little after, as it were the three ſupporters of <hi>Germany</hi> fell down. Firſt in the ſame Month the Earthquake was, <hi>viz. September</hi> the 25th. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> died, and 'tis ſtill freſh in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory what diſturbances enſued upon it, in the <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Miſnani</hi> Churches. Not many months after <hi>John Caſimir</hi> the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miniſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tor and Tutor of the Elector <hi>Palatin</hi> died, who came behind none of the moſt Valiant Heroes. And Laſtly, <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Lantgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe.</hi> The loſs of which three Princes in ſo ſhort a time, all prudent Men thought ominous to <hi>Germany,</hi> as they do ſtill, for that <hi>Germany</hi> ſeem not yet either to have ſhamn'd or overcome that Omen. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I here mention thoſe Wars which <hi>Moſchus</hi> again in the ſame year ſtirred up in <hi>Lifland</hi> and <hi>Sweedland,</hi> nor the death of thoſe Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Men <hi>Francis Hottoman, Cujavus,</hi> and ſome others, nor that which happened in <hi>France,</hi> the Siege of <hi>Paris,</hi> which continued for many months together, neither will I mention that two years after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>viz.</hi> in 92. ſeven other <hi>German</hi> Princes beſides <hi>Caſimir</hi> of Excellent Memory, were taken out of this World, and that a War aroſe between the two Elect Biſhops of <hi>Labert,</hi> while the Canor's diſſagreed about it; and that in the ſame year, <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. was choſen Pope, who was formidable for his craft and cunning. Which things ſeeing they are all thus experienced, let us ſtir up our minds to ſerious and ſervent Prayers, and to the Obſervation of the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrous Omens of the laſt Earthquake, and while we are deprecating the Portenta, let us prepare our ſelves for future Evils and the fatal change of <hi>Europe,</hi> foretold us by this Earthquake, and foreſeen by Wiſe Men. For it is poſſible either to ſhun decreed miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes either publick or private, or to render them more mild by piety, reaſon, due remedies applied from Counſel, and by o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing good contraty to thoſe Evils. But let us conſider that there are two ſorts of Motions in the Spirit of Mankind. There are ſome motions in the good Spirits, and ſome in the ill-natured and wicked ones. And as it happeneth that the illnatured Spirit do ſtir themſelves for the ruine and deſtruction of the beſt ſetled and ordered Kingdoms and Empires. So it happeneth often that God ſtirs up ſome profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and convenient Motions in the Spirits of the greateſt Princes, or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60606:20"/>in the Republicks, wherewith all the evil deſign; and machinations of the wicked are happely broken, and a good Peace and Tranquillity is procured as well to theſe Kingdoms, as to the Church. To which we may refer this great Revolution lately happened in this Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A little before this Earthquake which happened in <hi>France,</hi> in 1601. the <hi>Dauphine Lewis</hi> the XIII. was born in that Kingdom, and at the very hour of it the late Elector <hi>Palatin</hi> had his Son born.</p>
               <p>It is commonly ſaid, that motions of Heroick-ſouls are great and eaſie. Neither is Hiſtory defective in Examples of the Birth of great Heroes and Princes born juſt at the time, when there were Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes. Writers, ſays <hi>Hercules,</hi> was born whileſt the Earth was ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing although I am not ignorant what credit is to be given to the Hiſtory of <hi>Hercules;</hi> yet this is apparent from the Relation, that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients thought that an Earthquake was an Omen and Preſage of a great and Heroick-ſoul in thoſe whoſe birth happened at the ſame time. But there are other Examples of Earthquakes extant in Hiſtory, by which God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th (as by a portentum) atteſted his wrath againſt the enemies of the Righteous, and his favour to the Godly, by ſome joyful Omen. <hi>Theodorus, lib.</hi> 5. Hiſt. <hi>cap.</hi> 34. about the year 402. mentions, that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> was baniſhed by the Emperour <hi>Arcadius,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the firſt Night after his departure, the Emperours Palace was ſhaken by ſome terrible an Earthquake, that being frightned by that prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, he ſent Meſſengers after him, and honourably received him, whom he had ignominiouſly thruſt out. And <hi>Ruffinus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 28. Writes that <hi>Julian</hi> and Jews were terrified from repairing the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by a dreadful Earthquake, which they were earneſtly endeavouring to effect before, out of hatred and ignominy to Chriſt. So God diſcovered his anger againſt <hi>Diocletian</hi> the Cruel Perſecutor of the Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtians, by an Earthquake, in which many thouſand Men periſhed. <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 2. Hiſt. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. when a Councel was held at <hi>Antioch,</hi> where the Decrees of the <hi>Nicen</hi> Synod and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> were condemned by <hi>Arrians,</hi> not long after enſued a moſt grievous Earthquake, which laſting a whole year, was very deſtructive to <hi>Antioch A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>no</hi> 347 related by the <hi>Tripar.</hi> Hiſt <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Evagriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lib</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>Funccius</hi> in the year 344. and memorable in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tropius</hi> notes about the time the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie and Tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nny ſpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d through the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> that there were frequent Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes, and that thoſe places ſhook grievouſly. Neither is that which the ſame A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thor relates leſs remarkable, that preſently after the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60606:20"/>Death of the Apoſtles <hi>Paul, Laodicea,</hi> and <hi>Colloſſus</hi> were ſwallowed up by an Earthquake, ſo that the puniſhement of thoſe that contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Doctrine of <hi>Paul,</hi> might be conſpicuous. And I ſeem not to have ſpoken raſhly, when I ſaid that no puniſhment or calam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty is more grievous than an Earthquake, ſeeing 'tis an evil that can neither before ſeen, nor eaſily averted by any Remedies. <hi>Pliny. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 82. preſcribes two Remedies againſt Earthquakes, <hi>viz.</hi> to dig many holes in the Earth, and make many paſſages there; but this is both labourious and almoſt as dangerous to Cities and Towns, as an Earthquake. But perhaps ſome body will ſay, we ſhall be ſafe in Rivers againſt Earthquakes. I confeſs there is ſome ſafety in Rivers, and <hi>Synecius</hi> whom I cited before, Writ is that in a great Earthquake; he thought the Sea more ſecure than the Land; but that doth not want its dangers neither; for the bottoms of Rivers are obnoxious to Earthquakes, as we ſhall ſhew in our Problems, and the Earth may eaſily gape under the Water or ſome heap of Earth plunged into the River from the Neighbouring ſhore, may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm us, and ſometimes Rivers us'd to be dried by Earthquakes, ſo that they that ſeek ſafety in the Rivers againſt an Earthquake, may find their Death and Grave. But I cannot conjecture what ſhould be the meaning of that which <hi>Agathias, lib.</hi> 5. ſays, is the true Platonic Opinions, that he that periſhed by an Earthquake is to be eſteemed more happy than he that ſaved from it. For if an Earthquake be a moſt grievous puniſhment, which the Scripture atteſts, he cannot be happy who is involved in an Evil, grievous in it ſelf, and terrible to all Mankind.</p>
               <p n="75">75. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Scripture ſpeaks of an Earthquake as of a Sign or the forerunner of the laſt decretorial Judgment, at which a little before the end of the World, that great Judge will appear with the Angels of his Power, who himſelf, ſay <hi>Luke</hi> 21.11. That there will be great Earthquakes in every place before his coming; And <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.7. He makes uſe of almoſt the ſame Words. The Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of future Signs, reſpects both the deſtruction of the Temple and City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the end of the World. Therefore that which is aſſerted of great Earthquakes, may be accommodated to both thoſe times. For <hi>Joſephus</hi> diligently obſerves how great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes preceded the laſt ſacking of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="76">76. Of this ſorts of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> good Men think that was, of which we are now treating, by which the Son of God in this laſt Age of the World, would warn and excite Mens minds, that they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60606:21"/>might ſeriouſly and timely prepare themſelves for the great Seſſions, and hear that Sentence either of Eternal Life or Death, never to be revoked. I ſee no reaſon why we ſhould doubt that ſome Signs nearer and greater forerunners of the coming of Chriſt to Judgment than others. And therefore although this Earthquake be to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among thoſe Signs, as the ingenious and learn'd Mr. <hi>Beverly</hi> elegantly inſinuates, yet 'tis likely there will be ſome other Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake more terrible, meerly miraculous and nearer the Day of Judgment. Which he may be applied to other Signs, as darkning of the Sun and Moon, may be gathered from 24 of <hi>Matth.</hi> and 21 of <hi>Luke,</hi> and from <hi>Acts</hi> 2.19. where <hi>Peter</hi> cites that of <hi>Joel, I will give Miracles in Heaven above, and Signs in the Earth below; Blood, and Fire, and the Vapour of the Smoak. The Sun ſhall be changed into Darkneſs, and the Moon into Blood, before that great and glorious Day of the Lord comes,</hi> &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>. <hi>Thou Lord Jeſus come, com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quickly, or if it ſeems good to thee to delay, grant that while the Earth ſhakes and Hell rages, while Kingdoms, Empires, and Kings are ſhaken and daſhed one againſt the other; the Church, thy little Flock may enjoy, at leaſt a moderate quiet and reſt both here in</hi> England, <hi>and throughout the whole World.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the likeneſs or unlikeneſs of theſe two Earthquakes.</head>
               <p n="77">77. IT remaineth now, that we may examine, in what theſe two Earthquakes do agree, and in what they do differ, as well in their Forms and Cauſes, as in their Effects.</p>
               <p>As to the Form, 'tis ſaid in the 15th. <hi>Theorem,</hi> that the firſt was partly trembling and partly pulſative, according to the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the plainneſs or unplainneſs of the Fields. But all do agree, that this laſt was ſome kind of panting or brandiſhing Motion, for the Earth was ſhaken lateraly according to its Latitude; now that don't befall ſo in the Pulſe or Vibration; and that ſort of Earthquake is more frequent. Upon the laſſing of the firſt all Authors do not agree: But as to this laſt, 'tis Witneſſed from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60606:21"/>all places, that it did laſt two Minutes. I will only mention theſe words of Mr. <hi>Edward d' Auvergne,</hi> Chaplain to my Lord <hi>John Bathe,</hi> Governour of the Cittadel of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> in his Relation of the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>markable Tranſactions of the laſt Campaign, in the Confederate Army, where he was, pag. 61. <hi>We felt an Earthquake,</hi> ſays he, <hi>which laſted about two Minutes, and ſhook the Earth very violently. It was felt at the ſame time all over</hi> Flanders, <hi>in many parts of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> France, <hi>and in other places of</hi> Europe, <hi>we had it about two of the Cloek: It cauſed a great Conſternation in our new Gariſon of</hi> Dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muyde; <hi>ſome thinking at firſt that the</hi> French <hi>had undermined ſeveral parts of the Town, and were in Ambuſcades, going to blow them up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="78">78. We may obſerve among the other Conformities of theſe two Earthquakes, theſe two chiefly; the Conformity of the Month; and the Conformity of the Day. Nay, we ſhould make ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Time on the Day on both, to wit, that the firſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened at two of the Clock in the Morning; the laſt at two of the Clock in the Afternoon, ſo 'tis only the intercalation of 12 hours; which Event is remarkable enough. But now in regard of the Conformity of the Month: We have obſerved in the 45 <hi>Theorem,</hi> that amongſt the Planets, the Efficacy of <hi>Saturn</hi> did prevail that year. The ſame is happened this laſt year; as 'tis clear by the Obſervations of Mr. <hi>John Partridge,</hi> that Famous Mathematician, upon the Month of <hi>September:</hi> He ſays ſo, the Month of <hi>September</hi> begins with Quartile of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi> The Trine <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> with a wet and windy Air. <hi>2dly.</hi> 'Tis obſerved in the 46 and 47 <hi>Theorems,</hi> that the Power of the three ſuperious Planets, <hi>Saturn, Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> is the moſt eminent in producing Earthquakes. Beſides 'tis conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed, that the firſt Earthquake happened when the Sun was in <hi>Virgo.</hi> So were all theſe things diſpoſed at the time of this laſt Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake. Theſe are the very words of our forementioned Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician. <hi>All the mutual Aſpects of the Planets in this Month are</hi> Sol <hi>and</hi> Virgo, Luna <hi>and</hi> Libra, Saturnus <hi>and</hi> Sagittarious, Jupiter <hi>and</hi> Gemini. Mars <hi>in</hi> Libra, Venus <hi>in</hi> Virgo, Mercurious <hi>in</hi> Libra, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer <hi>in</hi> Libra. <hi>At laſt he doth conclude thus his Obſervations upon that Month. The Quartile of the</hi> Sun <hi>and</hi> Saturn, <hi>and the</hi> Sun <hi>and</hi> Jupiter, <hi>will in ſome meaſure influence</hi> September <hi>alſo,</hi> &amp;c. To which we may joyn, the Temper of the Air in that very Month; whoſe firſt part was warm and wet by turns; but the moſt part warm and windy: ſo if we confer theſe things with what is ſaid in the 52 and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60606:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60606:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60606:23"/>53 <hi>Theorems,</hi> we ſhall ſee that the Diſpoſitions of the Air were the ſame, to wit, rainy Wheather in the <hi>Dog-days.</hi> There was alſo a very high <hi>South-weſt</hi> wind in that Month, tho 'tis true that the Air was calm enough that very day when the Earth was ſhaken. <hi>Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> As theſe two Earthqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes had their Conformities in their Cauſes, ſo had they in their Effects, though not in ſuch a high degree. 'Tis obſerved that there are three Effects proceeding from Earthquakes.
<list>
                     <item>1. Univerſal Sickneſs.</item>
                     <item>2. Overflowing of Rivers</item>
                     <item>3. Scarcity of Fruit or Barrenneſs.</item>
                  </list>
As to the firſt, we did hear from many parts of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> that ſome Malignant Feaver did appear, and 'twas reported that ſome kind of Plague hath been diſcovered in the Province of <hi>Languedoc.</hi> We muſt adore the Divine Providence, who hath kept this Kingdom from all theſe Miſchiefs, wherein it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved by ſo many Sickneſſes, when the firſt Earthquake happened, in the laſt year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as to the overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Rivers, we had lately too many proofs of this effect; ſo that I need not to enlarge in the recital of many particular miſchances that happened in many places almoſt overwhelmed, where ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have been loſt by the Flood.</p>
               <p>We ſhould now come to examine the third effect of Earthquakes in reference to the firſt, that is the ſcarcity and barr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nneſs. But we leave it to be felt and proved in <hi>France,</hi> where we know it is great. And though all ſorts of Proviſions are grown ſo dear ſince the Month of <hi>December</hi> laſt, in this Kingdom, and eſpecially in <hi>London,</hi> yet that cannot be call'd ſcarcity; every one knows well enough the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between dearneſs and ſcarcity. The continuance of bad Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may always cauſe the ſame effect without any former Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake. We hope then that the ſame Divine Mercy which has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this Kingdom, and gathered therein ſo many thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Souls, and provided them with Bread ſeven years long by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, will continue to ſend the ſame Bleſſings of Plenty unto this Nation, who hath pitied his diſtracted People: The paſt Events being a kind of Security for the future. Whereupon we truſt that God will ſpare theſe Iſlands, wherein the Candleſtick of his Goſpel, hath been kept faſt, againſt all the Attempts of Popery. And ſo we conclude that the ſeven paſt years of Plenty are obſervable enough to put us in mind of the extraordinary and miraculous Providence of God for our Relief in a ſtrange Land: So 'tis to be feared alſo that his deſign hath been to warn us by this preſent dearneſs, to be wary afterward, and to turn our ſelves from any abuſing profuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60606:23"/>of his Graces; otherwiſe the Bread ſtaff of ſhall certainly be broken, it will be without ſtrength; <hi>'Tis the threatning he makes by Ezekiel againſt the Land which hath ſinned and grievouſly treſpaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him,</hi> Ezek. 14.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Some Problems as a Corollary both General and Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, which ſeem Naturally to riſe from this Matter.</head>
               <p n="1">1. VVHether that be true which <hi>Pliny</hi> aſſerts, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. that <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> are ſeldom ſhaken, by reaſon of the cold of the one and the heat of the other.</p>
               <p>'Tis certain that in there the cold and <hi>Northern</hi> Countries, Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes are more rare, becauſe the Earth being not ſo porous and looſe, doth not ſo eaſily open a paſſage for the Wind, which is confirmed by <hi>Olans Magnus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. But yet <hi>Northern</hi> Countries are not free from Earthquakes, which Hiſtory and Experience abundantly teſtifie. For in the year 1572. about the 6th. of <hi>January,</hi> a grievous Earthquake ſhook many both publick and private Buildings, in the County of <hi>Boruſſia,</hi> to their great damage. And in the year; 1200. a great Earthquake threw down many Houſes every where through <hi>Poland,</hi> as is related among others by <hi>Funccius, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Chro.</hi> And even <hi>Sweedland</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> have felt Earthquakes; ſo that <hi>France</hi> which is more meridional and hotter, cannot be free from Earthquakes. And altho' Vapours and Winds are not eaſily generated in hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and if they are, they are eaſily diſſolved, yet are theſe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with Earthquakes. 'Tis true ſome write of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that there never was any Earthquake, becauſe 'tis compoſed of the Mud that Nile when it overflows carries along with it, and ſo fitted to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, that the Spiritus can find no Receptacles. Yet <hi>Seneca, Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Natur. quaeſt.</hi> ſays he dares affirm againſt the Authority of great Men, that <hi>Egypt</hi> is ſometimes ſhaken. And there is a remarkable Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation extant, concerning this in <hi>Agathias, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Hiſt. Fol.</hi> 435. Where he ſays, <hi>About that time in the great City</hi> Alexandria <hi>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tuated by the River, an Earthquake was felt, which was ſhort and ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll, which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60606:24"/>all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Inbabita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts (eſpecially the more Ancient) eſteemed as a great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe there never was any before, yet all being aſtoniſh'd at the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul and ſudden C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntingency; for fear came all out, which fear alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne, who was there for the ſake of Laws and Litterature.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe that talk according to the Nature of things ſay, that <hi>Egypt</hi> can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot be filled with Vapours ſeeing it is low even, but that Opinion was then diſcovered to be weak. At the ſame time the Iſland of <hi>Cos,</hi> in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nfines of the <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea were ſhaken by an Earthquake, but a little part thereof was preſerved, the reſt being levelled to the Ground, and variouſly and almoſt beyond Credit afflicted with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion; and when I did navigate from <hi>Alexandria</hi> to <hi>Bizancy</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing carried by chance to that Iſland, ſuch a lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Sight did fall under my Eyes, that it cannot be expreſſed by Words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo ſays <hi>Agathyas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Why Rivers decreaſe by Earthquakes? <hi>Pliny, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other Effects of Earthquakes, mentions the adverſe Courſes of Rivers, others ſay backwards, becauſe they underſtand it, as if Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ran back to their Fountains, by reaſon of the lifting up of the Earth in the Channel, which obliges the Rivers to a retrograde Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis commonly experienced that Rivers are leſſened and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably decreaſed by Earthquakes for the firſt days, which is within a few Months after followed by an Inundation. <hi>Ruſa</hi> by <hi>Lucern,</hi> no contemptible Riv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> was ſo leſſened by an Earthquake in that place, where it firſt delivers it ſelf out of the Lake, and where it uſed to be the deepeſt, that the bottom thereof ſhewed it ſelf, and did not recover it ſelf in <hi>October,</hi> which is accounted by the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants as a Wonder. About the time of the late Earthquake, there was obſerved a remarkable decreaſe in the River <hi>Necker,</hi> which the great Rain that fell before in <hi>June, July,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt</hi> could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. And remarkable is that which <hi>Albertus Magnus, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Met. tract.</hi> 2. writes, That <hi>Necker</hi> River in <hi>Sweedland</hi> was ſwallowed up by an Earthquake, ſo that for one day it appeared not for a Mile to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. So we read in that Earthquake which happened under <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſius,</hi> in the year 400. that were going to paſs the Sea were ſeen ſtanding on dry Land. And in the year 1536. about <hi>Joppa,</hi> in the Government of <hi>Judea,</hi> the Sea retired from the Shoar for 3 Miles, and the bottom of it remained dry 3 days, and the River <hi>Jordan</hi> 2 days, but after it came to the Shoar again, the River ebbed again with a full Channel, and the Waters of both of them were bloody, as is related by <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or. Agricol. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de natura eorum quae effluant è terra,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60606:24"/>pag. 140. There may be a threefold Cauſe aſſigned for this according to the ſeveral ſorts of Earthquakes, for either the Fountains or Springs are obſtructed by the Trembling, and by the heap of Earth thrown upon them, whereby the Fountain being ſtopt there, the Vein of Water ſprings up in another place, as <hi>Geor. Agricol.</hi> relate of that Earthquake that ſhook the City of <hi>Scalpra,</hi> which we ſpoke of before, that a Sulphurous Fountain broke out of a Neighbouring Mountain. And <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> atteſts that new Fountains diſcover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d themſelves whilſt the Mountain of <hi>Aucto</hi> was ſhaken by an Earthquake. And an Earthquake did cauſe <hi>Lados,</hi> a River of <hi>Arcadia</hi> to ſpring up. And in the <hi>Mithridatick</hi> War, not only Lakes and Marſhes, but new Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Rivers ſprang up by <hi>Apamea</hi> a City of <hi>Phrygia,</hi> the old ones having been ſwallowed up by the Earthquake: See <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or. Agri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. de nat. rer. efflu. è terra</hi> pag. 151. Alſo while the Vapours burſt out of the Earth with great force, they ſo dilate and looſen the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſandy bottoms and ſides of the Channels, that the Water of the River is ſucked within the Earth, or laſtly, the Channels of the Rivers being elevated by the Pulſus, turn the Waters b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck again, ſo that they are received into the Gaverns of the Earth. That which is aſſerted of the ſtopping of Earthquakes by the tract of Rivers, is not uſual in any places where the Bottoms and Banks of Rivers are very porous and gravelly, when there is no Vapour ſtirring, but that which is very near the Superficies of the Earth, ſo that being rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the hardeſt parts of the Earth, which it could not penetrate, 'tis carried to the River-banks, which by reaſon of their poroſity yielding a Paſſage it ſooner exhales.</p>
               <p>But when the Channels of Rivers are more ſolid and rocky, and when the Wind that moves, is deeper within the Earth; and laſtly, when the coldneſs of the Water is an hindrance to the exhaling of the Vapours, Earthquakes ſtop not at Rivers, but gather ſtrength and impetuouſly rage under the Earth, which is noted by <hi>Pliny, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap</hi> 8. where he ſays, <hi>That thoſe who ſail in a Calm, eaſily gueſs when there is an Earthquake by the ſudden ſwelling or ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aking of the Wave, and thoſe things that are in the Ships ſhake as much as in Houſes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it by the noiſe they make; neither can the Birds ſit without ſhaking and fear.</hi> Which was lately experienced and atteſted by thoſe who were upon the <hi>Necker</hi> and the <hi>Rhine</hi> the 8th. of <hi>September,</hi> eſpecially by the Fiſhermen. whoſe Boats were ſtrongly aſſailed by the Vapours falling out of the bottom of the River, and Bubbles aroſe on the top of the Water, which is a certain Indication of the Combat of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60606:25"/>Water with the Vapours at the bottom of the River, and the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt propulſion of the Rivers in the manner of a Wave; ſometimes to this Bank, ſometimes to the other, diſcovered the Trembling and Viba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of the bottom. So 'twas obſerved in that grievous Earthquake, which ſhook <hi>Ferrara</hi> in the year 1570. that the River <hi>Po</hi> was much troubled by the leaping of Bubbles into the Air: which much con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irms me in the Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> propounded before of the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Vapours that cauſed the late Earthquake's great extenſion and velocity: for the Vapours that is but ſhallow, quickly exhales through the Channels of Riv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, ſo that neither rages nor is percepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble there, as is in like manner argued by the renowned B. <hi>Aretius, Prob.</hi> 172. where he thus writes; <hi>On the</hi> 6th. <hi>of</hi> April 1569. <hi>an Earthquake happened in many places;</hi> for 'tis apparent 'twas at the ſame time at <hi>Bern,</hi> at <hi>Thunn,</hi> at <hi>Strati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>burg</hi> and many interjacent places, and that which is worthy of our admiration is, it ſhook both the Banks of the River, when at other time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it hath been obſerved Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hquakes uſed to end at Rivers: Whence it may be gathered its riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was very deep.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Why are thoſe places that are either lying upon, or encompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Sea or ſome River obnoxious to Earthquakes, as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> ſays, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Metor. cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Earthquakes are moſt violent in thoſe places that the Sea runs by, where the Country is looſe and hollow, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the</hi> Helleſpont, Achaia, Eubaea, Sicily, <hi>for the Sea ſeems to run under the Ground through the</hi> Straits <hi>about thoſe places:</hi> Neither is that place at the end of the ſame Chapter contradictory to this; <hi>for,</hi> ſays he, <hi>there are no Earthquakes in the Iſles of</hi> Pontus, <hi>(for ſo is the Word to be rendred, and not in the Marine Iſlands) or very rarely.</hi> He only inſinuate; there, that there are not ſo violent ones, as in other Iſlands, by reaſon of the cold of the Sea verging to the <hi>North,</hi> by which the Vapours are thickned and made lumpiſh. <hi>Pliny</hi> follows <hi>Ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otle,</hi> who took moſt of what he hath of Earthquakes out of him, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>de ortu Subter. pag.</hi> 29. where he ſays, <hi>The Mountainous and Marine places are more eſpecially infeſted with Earthquakes, becauſe they abound w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th Veins and Caverns made by the Subterraneous Rivulets, that ſecretly disburthen themſelves into the Sea, or Lakes that are under the Mountains.</hi> And experience teaches us, that <hi>Cyprus, Sicily, Eubaea, Mollucca,</hi> and thoſe other Iſlands called <hi>Teritae</hi> are often grievouſly ſhaken by Earthquakes, which <hi>Bernardin Scalantus</hi> and others relate of the Iſlands <hi>China:</hi> And the reaſon is manifeſt, becauſe thoſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnous and porous places intercept the Humours in their Cavities,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60606:25"/>of which, Vapours are engendred, which when they endeavour to ſally out, are obſtructed by the Waves of the Sea, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey are again hid in the Bowels of the Earth, the cold on every ſide encloſing them and hindring their evaporation, ſo that being agita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by this confl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t, that is, heated and attenuated, they muſt neceſſarily ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke the Earth. Neither are Iſlands only, but the Continent alſo, obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to Earthquakes, though not in Campaign places, which are ſeldom ſhaken, becauſe they commonly have Caverns, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerved in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as <hi>Georg. Agricol. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de effluentibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>terra</hi> obſerves.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Baſill,</hi> in that part that borders on the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, or a great River are examples of this; the one of which of all the <hi>European,</hi> and the other of all the <hi>German</hi> Cities, is moſt infeſted with Earthquakes, as we ſhewed before of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> out of <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi>'s Hiſtory; but <hi>Procopious</hi> plainly atteſts, that <hi>Conſtantino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le</hi> ſhook for forty days together in the year 554. and in the year 740. it was ſhaken twelve months together, beginning on the 7th. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> as is noted among others by <hi>Funccius.</hi> But in later Ages evea in our own and Fathers memory, we have heard of frequent Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes in that City, which was felt by A. <hi>Gilpin Busbequiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> among others, and writ by him in the Epiſtles of his <hi>Turkiſh Embaſſy.</hi> And <hi>Stumpſius</hi> and others have writ, how often and grievouſly <hi>Baſill</hi> hath been ſhaken. <hi>Benedictus Arretius</hi> in the aforeſaid Problem reckons up ten times, that <hi>Baſill</hi> was ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken with great danger and loſs in the ſpace of 800 Years. <hi>In the Years</hi> 801, 824, 829, 1021. <hi>when the whole City was almoſt deſtroyed, the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch with many Houſes being thrown into the</hi> Rhine. And again, in the Year 1062, when a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Plague enſued upon the Earthquakes, again in the Year 1356: on the 18th. of <hi>October</hi> it ſhook ten times about Evening, ſo that the Church, Walls, Towers, and a great part of the City being deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it, there were a 100 Men killed. <hi>Stumpſius</hi> ſays, <hi>Liv.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 28. <hi>That the Earthquake continued all that year, and that</hi> Baſill <hi>ſhook ten times in an hour.</hi> In the following Year 1357. there happened another alſo in the Year 1444. as likewiſe in the Year 1456. it ſhook again; but in the Year 1533. moſt terribly, as we read in <hi>Munſter,</hi> not without great Commotion of Mind. The la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hquake was not a little perceived at <hi>Baſill.</hi> And <hi>Mentz</hi> hath ſometimes been d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly ſhaken by Earthquakes, and that thrice between the Year 855, and 880. and the firſt time the Walls and the Church of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> fell down. <hi>Conſtance</hi> alſo by the Lake of the <hi>Rhine</hi> trembled nineteen
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60606:26"/>times the ſame day, in the Year 1295. The People of <hi>Strasburg</hi> often ran to their Tents out of the City, by reaſon of the danger they were under from an Earthquake, eſpecially in the Year 1357. But I think there is no City upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> or in <hi>Germany,</hi> that is more frequently or dangerouſly ſhaken than <hi>Baſill;</hi> the reaſon whereof a Traveller ſeriouſly thought, when he was viewing its Scituation, than which a more pleaſant one he never had ſeen, nor was like to ſee, and he thus conſidered with himſelf, that the Cauſe of ſo great and ſo many Earthquake in that place was partly common with other Cities ſeated by Rivers, and partly proper and peculiar to that place. The common Cauſe is, that the River paſſing by the City makes the Earth chinky, and then pours in Water into thoſe Caverns it hath made, which deeply penetrating the Earth, engenders Vapours which being obſtructed by the cold of the Water, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, cannot evaporate, but being kept within the Earth longer time and varicuſly agitated, are turned into blaſts and winds adapted for Earthquakes, but the peculiar and proper Cauſe of Earthquakes in that City is; firſt, becauſe the <hi>Rhine</hi> is there narrower and more contracted, and being thus impriſonned, ſeeing it cannot overflow the Banks, it is carried more impetuouſly, the force of the Water being contracted within it ſelf, and as it were, by undermining it makes the deepeſt places of the Channel and Banks hollow and more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernous than in other places; ſo that more Vapours are apt to be generated and tarry there where they ſind a receptacle, being alſo encloſed and ſhut in by the cold of the Water or River. Another Cauſe is the many Dens and Caverns that are in a high Hill by the <hi>Rhine,</hi> adapted for the reception of Vapours, the Paſſage of which is eaſie and plain through the Pores of the Earth leading to the <hi>Rhine.</hi> To which may be added that this Hill ſcituate on the <hi>Rhine,</hi> whereon a great part of the City is built, hath every where a ſolid Superficies which is ſtony, ſo that many Vapours being engendred by the River flowing by, and impriſonned within the porous and cavernous Earth, cannot conveniently exhale through thoſe ways which they naturally ſeek, but being denied a paſſage, and collected and coarcted by their ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and reciprocation, and ſo gathering ſtrength by their heat and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, they impetuouſly invade and ſhake that which hinders them from above, Laſtly, 'Tis probable there is much Subterraneous fire, where <hi>Baſill</hi> ſtands, or not far from thence, as there is at <hi>Baden,</hi> which is diſtant but one days Journey from <hi>Baſill,</hi> where there are many and great B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ths, as is uſual in ſuch places, Exhaltations
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60606:26"/>ſallying out of the Earth even under the Waters of <hi>Limage</hi> that flows by it, which grows hot at the bottom by the Subterraneous Exhalations, as is often ſelft by thoſe that go naked into that River. Moreover, reaſon it ſelf diſcovers, and the examples of flames often breaking out in an Earthquake teſtifie, what great power Subterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous fires have to move the Earth, if they be ſhut up within the Earth. So that <hi>Geor. Agricol.</hi> truly ſays, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de ortu &amp; cau. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. pag.</hi> 27. <hi>That hot places, and where there are many hot Vapours, are obnoxious to Earthquakes, becauſe Subterraneous fire is apt to beget a quantity of ſmoaky Exhalations ſooner than a little heat.</hi> Yet <hi>Baden</hi> that hath ſo much Subterraneous fire is ſeldom ſhaken, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Exhalations there break out in great quantity, through the looſer and thinner Superficies of the Earth in regular Ways and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to their Nature. And if the Superficies of the Earth were ſo diſpos'd at <hi>Baſill,</hi> that the hot Water, which are perhaps in the Earth could have a paſſage and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly into the open Air, their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours would exhale in a ſuitable way, and would be a certain reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt frequent and dangerous Earthquakes: Which ſince na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath denied, perhaps it might be effected by Art, by every where digging and opening Caves towards the City, which might exhale the preconceived Spiritus, which is obſerved in ſome Towns which are ſeldom ſhaken, having ſome Caves digged to make a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for the Water; which remedy <hi>Pliny</hi> preſcribes, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 82. <hi>But I hope, God who hath vouchſafed to commit the heavenly Doctrine and Academy as a precious pledge and gage to it, will hereafter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that remarkable City from thoſe grievous Concuſions whereby Cities uſe to be deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. What credit may one give to the Relation of <hi>Plato</hi> of the Iſland <hi>Atlantis</hi> drowned by an Earthquake? <hi>Pliny lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. where he ſays, <hi>an Earthquake took away all the Ground where</hi> Atlantick <hi>Sea is if we credit</hi> Plato. Which relation of <hi>Plato</hi>'s, that <hi>Pliny</hi> hints at, is extant in <hi>Timeus,</hi> where he boaſts of the Antiquity of the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who waged War for many thouſands of years before, with the Inhabitants of the Iſland <hi>Atlantis,</hi> which he ſays, <hi>was greater than all</hi> Africa <hi>and</hi> Aſia, <hi>and was afterwards buried in an Earthquake, the</hi> Atlantick <hi>Ocean being let in upon it.</hi> The Iſland <hi>Atlantis</hi> was ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in a great Gulph, which made it unnavigable by reaſon of the Mud of the Iſland that was ſuck'd in. Then that <hi>Atlantick</hi> Sea was Navigable, for it had an Iſland before its Mouth, which you call the Pillars of <hi>Hercules:</hi> Which Iſland was bigger than <hi>Lybia</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60606:27"/>and <hi>Africa</hi> together, from whence there was a paſſage to other Iſlands, and to all the Continent over againſt it, round about ſcituated near the vaſt Sea.</p>
               <p>There are thoſe that would erect two great Geographical Theſes from theſe Words of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ias. Firſt,</hi> That the <hi>America,</hi> or that which we call the New World was known to the Ancients, eſpecially to <hi>Plato. 2dly,</hi> That the firſt Inhabiters of it came from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent of <hi>Aſia</hi> into <hi>America,</hi> viz. by the <hi>Atlantick</hi> Iſle. To gain Credit to which Aſſertion of their own and the Authority of <hi>Plato,</hi> they make the Scituation of places ſo, that they ſay the Iſland <hi>Atlantis</hi> poſſeſſed a great part of that Sea that is now called the <hi>Atlantick,</hi> that the Iſlands to which they aſcended from <hi>Atlantis,</hi> were thoſe that are by the Marriners at this day called <hi>Barlovent, Cuba, Spaniſh,</hi> St. <hi>John Boiquen</hi> and <hi>Tamaica:</hi> From theſe places there was a way to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, now called <hi>Terra firma,</hi> and ſo to the Kingdom of <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>America.</hi> If you ask what that Continent is, which <hi>Plato</hi> ſays, is ſcituated about <hi>Pontus?</hi> They anſwer, <hi>'Tis that</hi> Southern <hi>Sea commonly called</hi> Sur, <hi>which is called</hi> Pontus, <hi>by</hi> Plato, <hi>in reſpect of its greatneſs, if compared with the</hi> Mediterranean <hi>and</hi> Atlantick <hi>Sea.</hi> Thoſe that more nearly conſider the thing it ſelf, and the Relation of <hi>Critias,</hi> think all this, is aſſerted more out of a too great deference to the Authority of <hi>Plato,</hi> than any probability in the thing it ſelf. For that which he aſſerts of the unnavigableneſs of it, by reaſon of the drawing of <hi>Atlantis</hi> in the Ocean, is refuted by frequent Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thither: and thoſe Wonders <hi>Critias</hi> relates of the Origin of <hi>Atlantis</hi> are altogether fabulous, as alſo of its uncredible felicity, and their waging War with the <hi>Europeans,</hi> of their Temple built in the length of a Furlong, whoſe external Parts were filled with Silver, the higheſt with Gold, and within there was in Ivory Arch chequered wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Gold, Silver, and Copper. What Ruines of <hi>Atlantis</hi> are now to be ſeen under Water, as he aſſerts? to wit, by thoſe that cannot ſail thither? but what Earthquake is ſo great, in which a Country big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> may be ſucked in? or what Sea is ſo great, that could ſwallow up ſo great a Country, ſo that its bottom can be ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dee by no Hummer, which Seamen atteſt. But ſay they, <hi>Critias</hi> tells <hi>Timens</hi> before, that his Diſcourſe would be wonderful, but yet true. But what if things anſwer not words? who would believe that to be true, where he ſays, <hi>That</hi> Neptune <hi>falling in Love with</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, <hi>had T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ins ſive times by h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, divided one Hill into five Orbs, two of Earth and three of Sea?</hi> and that the <hi>Atlantick</hi> Sea can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60606:27"/>its Name from nothing but <hi>Atlantis,</hi> is too weak to be credit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For there is the Mountain <hi>Atlas,</hi> in the middle of <hi>Manritania,</hi> from which it is called the <hi>Atlantick</hi> Ocean, as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſays, <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. Where he alſo aſſerts the little and contemptible Iſland <hi>Atlantis</hi> was ſcituated over-againſt that Mountain.</p>
               <p>Yet we muſt confeſs that oftentimes great part of the Earth is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up by an Earthquakes, Examples of which <hi>Pliry</hi> recites, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 91, 92. And not a few received their Birth from the ſame Cauſe, as Nature would be even with her ſelf, as <hi>Delos</hi> that received from thence its Name, <hi>Rhodes, Nea, Thera, Theruſia, Aanaria,</hi> which the <hi>Greeks</hi> call <hi>Pitheuſa,</hi> and three others not notified by any proper Names, of which the firſt riſes up among the <hi>Acolian</hi> Iſlands, the other near <hi>Crete,</hi> the third in the <hi>Toſcan</hi> Bay. Sometimes the Sea hath broke in upon the Land by an Earthquake: So <hi>Sicily</hi> was ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Italy, Cyprus</hi> from <hi>Syria, Eubaea</hi> from <hi>Baotia. Pliny, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 88. And perhaps <hi>England</hi> from <hi>France. Servius</hi> explaining that Verſe in <hi>Virgil, Et penitus toto diviſos orbe Britaunos,</hi> ſeems to be of this Opinion; formerly, <hi>ſays he, Britain</hi> was joined to the Continent; the Sea between <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Calice</hi> lifts it ſelf up ſo high, and is ſo cloſely contracted, that many are of Opinion, that the Ground being dug there let in the Sea that was before excluded, which is alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by <hi>William Cambden,</hi> that accurate Writer, in his <hi>Chorogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical</hi> Deſcription of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> yet he puts off that Queſtion from himſelf, as alſo another, which is, Whether Iſlands were before the Flood? Of which may be conſulted <hi>Benedictus Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donius,</hi> who writ a Deſcription of all the Iſlands of the World.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether exterior Wind entring the Earth from above is able to move it? Of which Opinion were not a few of the Ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers <hi>Archelaus Calliſthenes</hi> and <hi>Metrodorus Chius</hi> think that the Wind which enters the Earth through thoſe <hi>Foramina</hi> which lie open, either to the Sea or to the Air, is the Cauſe of Earthquakes. Yet <hi>Archelaus</hi> doth not explain by what paſſages the Wind that moves the Earth penetrates into it, either through thoſe ſecret ones that lie hid under the Sea, or through the open ones, or both. <hi>Calliſthenes</hi> was of Opinion, 'twas by the latent paſſages under the Sea. But <hi>Metrodorus</hi> thought the Wind fell from above on the Earth, which is included in the Caverns. So they both were of opinion, that ſome Wind inſinuated it ſelf into the Caverns of the Earth, which was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by more and more, which ſo preſſed and ſtraitned the former, that finding no <hi>exitus</hi> it turned its force againſt the Earth and ſhook it.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60606:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60606:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60606:29"/>Which opinion of the Ancients, <hi>Geor. Agricol lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de ort. ſubt.</hi> bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering to pieces, ſays, <hi>The exterior Wind doth not ſeem able to effect an Earthquake, becauſe its Particles entring into the vaſt Caverns are diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, or being contracted together have not ſo much force, for the Cold in ſo long a ſpace of Air extinguiſheth its heat. Ariſt. lib.</hi> 2 <hi>Meteor. cap.</hi> 7, and 8. makes no mention of exterior Wind, but aſcribes Earthquakes totally to the Vapours engendred within the Caverns of the Earth: In <hi>Lib. de Mund.</hi> if that be <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s, <hi>cap.</hi> 4. he thus writes: <q>It often happens that exterior Wind breaking into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of the Earth, being excluded any <hi>Exitus,</hi> by turning it ſelf within, ſhakes the Earth with great force;</q> which may I think be thus reconciled, if we ſay an Earthquake regularly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is cauſed by Vapours which are engendred within the Earth, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it may happen, that an exterior thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ker and moiſter Wind being as with a Whirl wind thruſt into the Caverns of the Earth, is mingled with the Subterraneous Vapours, and ſo conjoyntly with them ſhakes the Earth, when it could never ſeparately and by it ſelf. To this I will add, that thoſe that attribute Earthquakes to internal flatus, differ in their Opinions: for ſome ſay that the Earth being void of all Life and Senſe, hath ſome Spiritus engendred together with it, which Opinion, is conſtantly defended by <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> But there were others formerly who attributed ſuch a Life and Spiritus to the Earth, as in the bodies of Plants, and vital and animal Spirits, as there is in Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals; which Opinion is eſpouſed by one of the Phyſical Writers; all other Philoſophers that I have ſeen, are of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi>'s Opinion; as being moſt conſtant to reaſon and experience. For ſeeing the Earth is a Principle and Element of all mixt bodies, conſequently every mixt body would live; yea, the Earth would be no longer an Element if it had life, for living bodies have received their laſt complection and perfection, which cannot be aſſerted of Elements, which are deſigned by Nature for the conſtitution of fuller bodies, as the Principles of all mixt bodies. But let us ſee how the Earth is moved ſuppoſing it lives; as in the Body of Man, ſay thoſe, who are of that Opinion, when 'tis well, the Veins through which the Blood and Spiritus paſs, are not diſturbed, but when 'tis not well, they never leave panting: ſo the Earth, when 'tis in its natural ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, Vapours are quickly diffus'd through its Veins, is obnoxious to no Earthquakes: but when it hath not its own ſituation, and the Vapours intangled with Ruin and Mud, find not a free paſſage through the Veins, then there muſt neceſſarily happen a ſhaking of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60606:29"/>the Body of the Earth, ſo the Earth is therefore moved by them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis in a Feaver. <hi>Sene. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>natur. quaeſt.</hi> thus attacks that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: <hi>If,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Earth like an Animal is moved from this Cauſe, it will all feel vexation, for a Feaver in us doth not more moderately impel ſome parts and others more quickly, but runs through all with an equal degree.</hi> But Phyſicians will think this reaſon of <hi>Seneca</hi>'s weak; for one Member of an Animal may be infeſted <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with a tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or palpitation; ſo that if we grant the Earth lives: part of it may tremble and be ſhaken alone, for altho' it hath not either Nerves or Muſcles, yet it hath Veins and as it were Pipes on every ſide ſill'd with Spirits.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether Subterraneous Exhaltations are generated by the Sun Beams? <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> conſtant Opinion is, they are generated part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the heat of the Sun influecing them from above, partly by the heat of Subterraneous fire every where diſperſed through the Caverns of the Earth, as he ſpeaks, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Meteor. cap.</hi> 8. <q>The Earth of it ſelf, <hi>ſays he,</hi> is dry, but it receives great moiſture from Rains, which growing hot by the Sun and the heat in the Earth, begets much Vapours, both without and within the Earth;</q> which Opinion is therefore diſaproved of by <hi>Geor. Agricol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de ortu Subter. pag.</hi> 25. becauſe the Sun draws all the Vapours it begets out of the Earth. But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> will eaſily anſwer, <hi>That ſome Vapours are therefore heated by the Sun, that they may be drawn out; but ſome are engendred ſo deep within the Earth, that they cannot be drawn out.</hi> I confeſs heat draws moiſture to it ſelf; doth not drive it away, but it doth not draw out all its draws to it. Neither doth that preſently obtain the end that acts for an end. The Refiners of Metals and Mines fetched out of the Veins of the Earth, muſt needs, ſays <hi>Agricola,</hi> 
                  <q>To hew a Ditch on the Earth under the Crucible, to draw thither all dampneſs, for fear leſt otherwiſe, the ſtrength of fire drawing out the moiſtneſs of the Earth into the Crucible, it would grow ſwelled and burſt to pieces with ſudden loſs and ſquandering away of the Metal: If the heat doth draw to it ſelf the moiſtneſs, much more can it put in a motion an Exhalation, and draw to it a Vapour which is of the ſame kind with it ſelf.</q> This is true, yet they do not evince that, which they were to prove, that the heat of the Sun doth draw out preſently that Exhalation and ſet it at freedom, which it draws to it, that's not altogether in the power of the Sun, there are theſe things that detain that Exhalation engendred within the Earth, that it cannot fly whither it is drawn.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60606:30"/>
               <p n="7">7. Whether <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> for any certain Reaſons, appoints more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Earthquakes? We noted before in the 28 <hi>Theorem,</hi> that <hi>Ariſlotle</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of opinion that Earthquakes commonly happen about the Equinox, in <hi>Spring</hi> and <hi>Autum:</hi> but the accurate Searcher of Subterraneous things, <hi>Geor. Agric. pag.</hi> 29. is of another opinion; where, he ſays, Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n I examine his Reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> why Earthquakes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen oftner in <hi>Spring</hi> and <hi>Autumn,</hi> than in <hi>Summer</hi> and <hi>Winter,</hi> by night than day, in the night time at the breaking of the day oftneſt, in the day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime at noon, I find them weak and of little force, for he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes all to the Sun, which he doth becauſe, if it be without this, the Earth at all times of the year would have the ſame diſpoſition in it. <q>The Sun, ſays <hi>Agricola,</hi> cannot be the Cauſe, much leſs the Moon's Ecclipſe; becauſe if the preſence of the Sun conduced to this, more Earthquakes would happen in <hi>Summer,</hi> than in the <hi>Spring</hi> or <hi>Autumn;</hi> more in day time, than in the night; and if its ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence be influential, there would be more at midnight, than at break of day, in <hi>Winter,</hi> than in the <hi>Spring</hi> or <hi>Autumn.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> obſerved not that the ſcorching of the Sun heating the Earth, draws thoſe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours out of the Earth, not ſhats them in it, that were neither generated by it, or were touched by internal heat after their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. But this is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of which we diſputed in the preceding Problem. The Sun engenders Exhalations, which when they fly into the Air of their own accord, are ſaid to be drawn and extracted by the Sun, but I do not grant that (ſpeaking properly) the Sun draws forth Exhalations. But let us ſpeak as the cuſtom is, that the Sun doth draw Exhalations towards it, does it therefore draw them out of the Earth? <hi>Agricola</hi> excepts: <q>There is no ſtopping, <hi>ſays he,</hi> that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nders thoſe which the Sun produces; for it would not engender them unleſs its vertue could pierce into the upper part of the Earth, and the Sun excites the Exhalations out of the Earth, by the ſame way the power of the Sun penetrates into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arth, and ſo doth not impriſon them within the Earth.</q> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſees, how ready an Anſwer is for <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> 
                  <q>The Sun, ſays <hi>Agricola,</hi> would not beget Exhalations unleſs it could bring them forth out of the Earth, yea, it begets many not to extract them, but to afford matter for the generation of Metals within the Earth, as Gold, Silver, and alſo for the generation of Minerals, as Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, Brimſtone, whoſe form is ſo exeellent and profitable, that it may be called the end, for which that Celeſtial Body efficaciouſly operates in and under the Earth by its Rays.</q> But as we anſwered
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60606:30"/>before, Natural Agents are not ſo ordered, as always to attain the end of their operation, becauſe they act not deliberately, and cannot ſuſpend the Action. The Sun engenders Exhalations, by the innate power of its Rays, whither it be able to bring them into open Air or not, neither doth the eduction of them belong to the nature or perfection of the Sun, but of the Exhalation, whoſe natural (place, that is, that which it moſt deſires,) is in the Air. But ſeeing the frequency of Earthquakes both in <hi>Autumn</hi> and <hi>Spring</hi> is atteſted by the experience of all Times, what reaſon ſhall we aſſign for it, if that which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath given, is not available? <hi>Agricola</hi> anſwers, <hi>Becauſe the internal heat of the Earth ſometimes procreates many Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, ſometimes few, and where many are impriſoned, they cauſe Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes in all times of the year and day.</hi> But with the leave of ſo great a Man, this is nothing elſe than to ask what is in the Principle or in Queſtion; for why ſometime; more, ſometimes fewer Vapours are generated, is that, that is inquired after; which cauſe is not within the Earth, but altogether depends upon a Celeſtial Body, which as it is firſt, ſo it is moſt efficacious, both on the Earth and other Bodies.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Why are Birds frighted in an Earthquake, as is atteſted by <hi>Pliny, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 81. <hi>Birds alſo,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſit not without fear in an Earthquake?</hi> 'Tis no wonder if Terreſtial Animals are frighted, while the Earth trembles, but how can Birds, while they paſs through the Air, perceive what the Earth ſuffereth? Birds have a thin and ſubtil, that is to ſay, an airy conſtitution of body, ſo that they eaſily perceive every little alteration of the Air, and it is paſt doubt that the Air may be affected and altered by an Earthquake eſpecially in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and thoſe places where the Air is more thin the ſubtil.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whither the Vaults in Houſes are ſafeſt? <hi>Pliny</hi> doth affirm it in his <hi>2d.</hi> Book, <hi>cap.</hi> 83. <q>Where preſcribing Remedies and Aids againſt Earthquakes, he ſays, Vaults and corners of Walls and Poſts alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natively thruſting againſt one another;</q> where he ſpeaks, I believe, of Subterraneous Vaults, in which the Vapours being received in a more capacious place, do not rage ſo much, as in a narrow one; altho' a greater Percuſſion may be in a hollow and round place, than in a level. Thoſe Roof and Arches that are above the Earth, are not a little infeſted with Earthquakes: which we ſee by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the late Earthquake in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where the Roofs of many Churches were very much cracked. At <hi>Lucern</hi> the <hi>Francician</hi>'s
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60606:31"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60606:31"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60606:32"/>Church was ſo ſhaken, that the Roof hanging over the Chorus was ſo demoliſhed, that it muſt all be repaired a new: and no doubt many ſuch like things happened in other places by the ſame Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Was the late Earthquake ſo ended, that the Countries through which it went, are ſecure from its itteration? We obſerved before two ſorts of Earthquakes, ſome are continual, that is, either continually ceaſing or laſting; and ſome interrupted or itterated at diſtinct times. In the year 554. <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſhook forty days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as <hi>Procopius</hi> atteſts, and in the year 740. a great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake beginning on the 7th. of <hi>November,</hi> laſted there a whole year, as is obſerved by <hi>Funccius, pag.</hi> 128. <hi>Chro.</hi> But this, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve was an interrupted and not a continual one. In the year 480. as is related by <hi>Eutropiu, lib.</hi> 10. an Earthquake ſhook <hi>Germany</hi> a Month together. And remarkable is that which is related, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtor. tripar.</hi> In the year 344. an Earthquake ſhook firſt <hi>Antiochia,</hi> and then almoſt all the <hi>Eaſt</hi> a year together, when the preceding year the <hi>Arrian</hi> Faction aſſiſted with the protection of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> had moſt cruelly perſecuted both <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and the whole Orthodox Church, which we alſo mentioned before. In the 19th. year of <hi>Friderick</hi> the I. <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> begun, and afterwards continued for many years together to ſhake; ſome Towns being indamaged, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers demoliſhed, and a dreadful ſlaughter made of living Creatures, as, <hi>George Agricola</hi> relates, out of the Hiſtory of thoſe times, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de nat. efflu. è terra. pag.</hi> 151. where he adds, that an Earthquake happened at <hi>Seville</hi> and <hi>Cordoua</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> which laſted three years, which is very remarkable. In the year 741. twenty Earthquakes almoſt continued, ſhook <hi>Wiritzbourgh,</hi> as <hi>Funccius</hi> obſerves. In the year 1276. twelve Earthquakes ſhook <hi>Germany,</hi> there being but a little ſpace of time between them, as is witneſſed by <hi>Stump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fius, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. In the year 1295. an Earthquake was repeated at <hi>Conſtance</hi> 19 times. In the year 1531. a great Earthquake was itterated 8 times at <hi>Olyſippa</hi> or <hi>Lisburn,</hi> in <hi>Portugal.</hi> In the year 177. <hi>Baſill</hi> was ſhook 9 times in 9 months. That Earthquake which happened in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, was alſo interrupted, that is to ſay, was repeated; ſo that between the firſt and ſecond time (at which time it was not ſo vehement in theſe places as at the firſt) it interpoſed about a quarter of an hour.</p>
               <p>But that which was inquired after in the propounded Problem was, whither the matter of an Earthquake reaching ſo far was conſumed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60606:32"/>in thoſe two ſhakes. I would not here raſhly aſſert any thing, nor frighten my ſelf with ſiniſtrous Omens: I will only mention that, which if not neceſſarily, yet truly may be determined for Phyſical Principles of interrupted Earthquakes: I will lay the <hi>Theorems</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <hi>Firſt,</hi> When there happen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a great Earthquake, that reaches far and near, all the Vapours collected in the Earth ſhake it not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and at once, but are interrupted for forty days, then for a year, and ſometimes they threaten another Earthquake in the ſame place for two years; for Vapours may be contain'd ſo long within the Earth. This <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> aſſerts almoſt in ſo many words, which is alſo confirmed by the experience of theſe examples we have cited, and by ſuch others: which alſo <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> explains by a very apt Similitude; <hi>As the unnatural Pulſes in our Bodies,</hi> ſays he, <hi>do not preſently, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and interruptedly end with the Diſeaſe:</hi> ſo winds no not ſooner leave off ſhaking the Earth, than the Relicks of them are conſumed. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Phyſical <hi>Theorem</hi> is, That interrupted Earthquakes commonly return in a more vehement manner; for the longer the Vapour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends within the Earth, the ſtronger 'tis rendred. The third <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem</hi> is likely, That as <hi>Pliny</hi> writes of the Plague, <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 59. That it hath been a long time experienced, that it goes from Eaſt to Weſt, and if it happens otherwiſe, it every where prevails: So an Earthquake goes from the South to the North, from Eaſt to Weſt. This is alſo certain that there are two ſorts of Interruptions, one quick, when 'tis ſuddenly itterated, the other ſlow when 'tis repeated after many Days and Months. The laſt Earthquake had not any ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den renew all, but we have reaſon to fear a ſlow one. To which we may add that the Eclipſe of the Sun on the 27th. of <hi>December,</hi> threatens us with its effects, and the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Scorpio</hi> may add to it: of which this is their Rule; <hi>Saturn</hi> in <hi>Mars</hi> ſhakes the Earth, which Rule experience confirmed in the year 1542. when after the ſame Conjunction a great Earthquake ſhook <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> And there will be a Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>July,</hi> as there was in <hi>October</hi> 1531. when <hi>Portugal</hi> was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly ſhaken. But we muſt refer the care of futurities to God: 'Tis our duty to reſt on his eternal preſence, to correct paſt things, and live now more chaſtly and piouſly as Mr. <hi>Beverly</hi> learnedly and fervently exhorts in his Treatiſe of Trepidations of the Earth, <hi>pag.</hi> 132. which that we may do, God Almighty grant, who alone can move Mens Hearts as he doth the Earth.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
